片名: 霍比特人
亲爱的弗罗多
My dear Frodo:
你曾问过我...
You asked me once...
我是不是把全部探险经历都告诉你了
if I had told you everything there was to know about my adventures.
我只能说...
And while I can honestly...
我告诉了你...
say I have told you...
真相...
the truth...
但不是全部
I may not have told you all of it.
我老了 弗罗多
I am old now, Frodo.
不再是曾经那个霍比特人了
I'm not the same Hobbit I once was.
是时候...
I think...
让你知道...
it is time for you to know...
全部真相了
what really happened.
故事...
It began...
始于很久前...
long ago...
在遥远的东方...
in a land far away to the east...
现在已无处寻觅
the like of which you will not find in the world today.
有一座河谷镇
There was the city of Dale.
城里有知名的...
Its markets known...
大型市场
far and wide.
到处都是藤蔓和溪谷
Full of the bounties of vine and vale.
祥和富足
Peaceful and prosperous.
因为这座城市...
For this city lay before the doors...
横亘在中土最伟大的王国门外
of the greatest kingdom in Middle-earth:
伊鲁柏
Erebor.
最强大的...
Stronghold of Thror...
山下之王索尔...
King Under the Mountain. Mightiest...
的矮人王国
of the Dwarf Lords.
索尔有着绝对的统治权...
Thror ruled with utter surety...
从没有人质疑他王权的延续...
never doubting his house would endure...
因为他的统治...
for his line lay secure...
有他儿子...
in the lives of his son...
还有孙子来继承
and grandson.
啊 弗罗多 说到伊鲁柏
Ah, Frodo. Erebor.
它建在山脉内部...
Built deep within the mountain itself...
是座传奇般美丽的要塞
the beauty of this fortress city was legend.
它的财富埋藏在地下...
Its wealth lay in the earth...
岩石中随处可见宝石...
in precious gems hewn...
黄金像河水一样奔流...
from rock and in great seams of gold...
储量丰富
running like rivers through stone.
矮人们加工钻石 祖母绿...
The skill of the Dwarves...
红宝石 蓝宝石的技艺..
was unequaled, fashioning objects...
如同美人的饰物般...
of great beauty...
精湛得无与伦比
out of diamond, emerald, ruby and sapphire.
越挖越深...
Ever they delved deeper...
深入黑暗
down into the dark.
然后 在那里 发现了它
And that is where they found it.
山脉之心
The Heart of the Mountain.
阿肯宝石
The Arkenstone.
索尔取名为"国王的珠宝"
Thror named it "The King's Jewel. "
他把它当做一种象征...
He took it as a sign, a sign that his right to rule...
天赐统治权的象征
was divine.
所有人...
All would pay...
都要向他表示尊敬
homage to him.
包括伟大的...
Even the great...
精灵王 瑟兰督伊
Elven King, Thranduil.
随着矮人们的财富增长...
As the great wealth of the Dwarves grew...
他们的良知却日渐淡薄
their store of good will ran thin.
没有人知道争议究竟因何而起
No one knows exactly what began the rift.
精灵们说...
The Elves say...
是矮人们偷了他们的宝藏
the Dwarves stole their treasure.
矮人们则另有论断
The Dwarves tell another tale.
他们说是因为精灵王拒绝支付报酬
They say the Elf King refused to give them their rightful pay.
很可悲 弗罗多 长久的联盟...
It is sad, Frodo, how old alliances...
为何会分裂
can be broken.
人们之间的友谊会灭失
How friendships between peoples can be lost.
为何会灭失?
And for what?
渐渐的 日子不再好过...
Slowly the days turned sour...
暗夜即将来临
and the watchful nights closed in.
索尔对黄金的痴迷...
Thror's love of gold...
走火入魔
had grown too fierce.
他产生了邪念
A sickness had begun to grow within him.
那是心灵的邪念
It was a sickness of the mind.
而邪念滋生之处...
And where sickness thrives...
罪恶也随之而来
bad things will follow.
首先大家听到了...
The first they heard was a noise...
像飓风一样的声音...
like a hurricane coming down...
从北方袭来
from the North.
山丘上的松树...
The pines on the mountain creaked and cracked...
在炎热干燥的风中吱嘎碎裂
in the hot, dry wind.
巴林 发警报
Balin, sound the alarm.
召集守卫 快!
Call out the guard. Do it now!
怎么回事?
What is it?
龙
Dragon.
龙!
Dragon!
那是...
He was...
北方来的火龙
a firedrake from the North.
史矛革...
Smaug...
来了
had come.
那天死者...
Such wanton death...
不计其数
was dealt that day.
史矛革视人族城镇...
For this city of Men was nothing...
为无物
to Smaug.
他...
His eye...
另有目标
was set on another prize.
因为龙...
For dragons...
对黄金...
covet gold...
有非常狂热的...
with a dark and...
贪念
fierce desire.
啊!
Aah!
不!
No!
走啊
Come on.
伊鲁柏失陷
Erebor was lost.
因为龙...
For a dragon...
会守卫他的战利品...
will guard his plunder...
不死不离
as long as he lives.
逃命去吧!
Run for your lives!
啊! 帮帮我们!
Ah! Help us!
瑟兰督伊不会让自己的族人...
Thranduil would not risk the lives of his kin against...
冒性命之险去对抗龙的残暴
the wrath of the dragon.
那天精灵方未施援手...
No help came from the Elves...
从那以后再也没有
that day, nor any day since.
被赶出了自己的家乡...
Robbed of their homeland...
伊鲁柏的矮人们流离失所...
the Dwarves of Erebor wandered the wilderness...
曾经高傲的人们陷入困境
a once mighty people brought low.
年轻的矮人王子竭尽所能...
The young Dwarf prince took work where he could find it...
在人族村庄中劳作
laboring in the villages of Men.
但他一直没有忘记...
But always he remembered...
月下的山丘升起的黑烟...
the mountain smoke beneath the moon...
树木像火把一样燃炽
the trees like torches blazing bright.
因为他目睹了...
For he had seen dragon fire...
漫天的龙火...
in the sky...
将一座城市变为灰烬
and a city turned to ash.
他永远不会原谅...
And he never forgave...
也永远不会忘记
and he never forgot.
而在远方 在世界的另一个角落...
Far away, in another corner of the world...
龙只是...
dragons were...
存在于传说中
only make-believe.
飞上去喽!
Up they go!
在仲夏夜的聚会上...
A party trick...
由巫师变出来的...
conjured by Wizards...
魔术里
on Midsummer's Eve.
还不如魔法仙尘...
No more frightening...
可怕
than fairy dust.
比尔博!
Bilbo!
而我 亲爱的弗罗多...
And that, my dear Frodo...
就此参与了这段传奇
is where I come in.
比尔博! 比尔博
Bilbo! Bilbo.
一段伴随了我一辈子却有些意外的友谊...
It was the beginning of an unlikely friendship...
就是那样开始的
that has lasted all my life.
而并不是我故事真正的开始 对我来说 应该从...
But it is not the start of my story. For me, it began...
刚开始 可能跟你期待的一样
Well, it began as you might expect.
地上的洞穴里 住着一个...
In a hole in the ground, there lived...
霍比特人
a Hobbit.
并不是杂乱 肮脏 充满怪味和虫子的潮湿洞穴
Not a nasty, dirty, wet hole full of worms and oozy smells.
是个霍比特式洞穴
This was a Hobbit hole.
那就意味着高品质的食物 温暖的壁炉...
And that means good food, a warm hearth...
以及一切组成家的舒适条件
and all the comforts of home.
谢谢
Thank you.
这是什么?
What's this?
这是私人物品
That is private.
把你的手爪子拿开
Keep your sticky paws off.
还没准备好呢
It's not ready yet.
准备做什么?
Not ready for what?
给人看
Reading.
这些到底都是什么?
What on earth are these?
对聚会邀请函的回复
Replies to the party invitations.
啊 太好了 是今天吗?
Ah. Good gracious. Is it today?
他们都说会来
They all say they're coming.
除了塞克维尔巴金斯一家 他们要求你单独邀请
Except for the Sackville-Bagginses, who are demanding you ask them in person.
是吗 真的? 等我...
Are they, indeed? Over my...
- 死了吧  - 他们可能认为...
- dead body.  - They'd probably find that...
这样是可以的
quite agreeable.
他们好像认为你有些地道满藏着金子
They seem to think you have tunnels overflowing with gold.
只有一个小箱子 根本没满
It was one small chest, hardly overflowing.
还带着食人妖的味道
And it still smells of Troll.
你究竟在干什么?
What on earth are you doing?
预防措施 其实...
Taking precautions. You know...
我曾经有一次看到她带着银餐具走掉
I caught her making off with the silverware once.
- 谁?  - 罗贝莉娅・塞克维尔巴金斯
- Who?  - Lobelia Sackville-Baggins.
她把我所有的勺子都装进了她口袋里 哈!
She had all my spoons stuffed in her pocket. Ha!
讨厌的女人
Dreadful woman.
得留神盯着她 等我...
Make sure you keep an eye on her after I'm...
等我... 等我...
When I'm... When I'm...
等你什么?
When you're what?
没事了 没事
It's nothing. Nothing.
有些人开始对你很好奇了 叔叔
You know, some people are beginning to wonder about you, Uncle.
- 啊?  - 他们认为你变怪了
- Huh?  - They think you're becoming odd.
怪了? 哦 嗯
Odd? Oh. Hm.
孤僻
Unsociable.
我 孤僻? 开玩笑
Unsociable, me? Nonsense.
乖乖的...
Be a good lad and put that...
把这个钉到门上去
on the gate.
非宴会事宜 请勿入内
你觉得他会来吗?
Do you think he'll come?
谁?
Who?
甘道夫
Gandalf.
哦... 哈 他可不会放过能表演他的小把戏的机会 他会给我们...
Oh... ho. He wouldn't miss a chance to let off his Whizpoppers. He'll give us...
演一场好戏的 等着吧
quite a show, you'll see.
- 好吧 那么 我就走了  - 去哪?
- Right, then. I'm off.  - Off to where?
东区森林 我要去给他个惊喜
East-farthing Woods. I'm going to surprise him.
哦 那你去吧 你肯定不想迟到
Well, go on, then. You don't want to be late.
他没迟到 哦 不 我也...
He doesn't approve of being late. Oh, no. Not that I...
没迟到过
ever was.
那个时候 我总是很准时
In those days, I was always on time.
非常受人尊敬
I was entirely respectable.
我身上从没发生过...
And nothing unexpected...
意料之外的事情
ever happened.
意外之旅
60年前...
- 早上好  - 你什么意思?
- Good morning.  - What do you mean?
你是希望我早上好还是不管我想不想要...
Do you wish me a good morning or do you mean that it is a good morning...
我的早上都会好?
whether I want it or not?
或者你可能是想说这个早上你感觉非常好?
Or perhaps you mean to say that you feel good on this particular morning?
再或者你只是单纯的想表示这个早上会好? 嗯?
Or are you simply stating that this is a morning to be good on? Hm?
我觉得 以上全对
All of them at once, I suppose.
嗯
Hmm.
我能帮你吗?
Can I help you?
有待观察
That remains to be seen.
我在寻找人一起探险
I'm looking for someone to share in an adventure.
探险?
An adventure?
不 我觉得布理以西没有人会对探险感兴趣
No, I don't imagine anyone west of Bree would have much interest in adventures.
邋遢 烦人 不爽的事情
Nasty, disturbing, uncomfortable things.
让人吃不上晚餐 嘿嘿
Make you late for dinner. Heh, heh.
嗯
Mm.
哈
Huh.
嗯
Hmm.
哦 哈
Oh. Ah.
早上好
Good morning.
真没想到有一日 我会被贝拉多娜・图克的儿子...
To think that I should have lived to be "good morninged"...
用一句 "早上好" 打发走 就好像我是上门推销扣子的人
by Belladonna Took's son as if I were selling buttons at the door.
你说什么?
Beg your pardon?
你变了 可是并不是完全往好的方向...
You've changed, and not entirely for the better...
比尔博・巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins.
抱歉 我认识你吗?
I'm sorry, do I know you?
呃 你知道我的名字 可是你对不上号了
Well, you know my name, although you don't remember I belong to it.
我是甘道夫
I'm Gandalf.
甘道夫就是...
And Gandalf means...
我
me.
甘道夫? 不是那个能...
Gandalf? Not Gandalf the wandering Wizard...
能变非常棒的烟火的游者巫师...
who made such excellent...
- 甘道夫吧? 老图克经常在仲夏夜放那个  - 嘿嘿 嗯
- fireworks? Old Took used to have them on Midsummer's Eve.  - Heh, heh. Ahem.
不知道你还在干这个呢
No idea you were still in business.
那我应该干什么去了?
And where else should I be?
干什么...? 嗯
Where else...? Ahem.
呃 很高兴你还记得有关我的事情...
Well, I'm pleased to find you remember something about me...
虽然只记得我的烟火
even if it's only my fireworks.
对 是的 那就决定了
Yes. Well, that's decided.
这会对你很好...
It'll be very good for you...
让我觉得很有趣
and most amusing for me.
我应该通知其他人了
I shall inform the others.
通知谁? 什么? 不 不 不... 等等
Inform the who? What? No. No. No... Wait.
我们这的人不要...
We do not want...
探险 谢谢 今天不要 以后...
any adventures here, thank you. Not today. Not...
我建议你去山的那边或者海的对岸
I suggest you try Over the Hill or Across the Water.
早上好
Good morning.
早上好!
Morning!
十二个钱 给您 祝您愉快
Twelve. There we go. Have a very good day.
谢谢
Chum.
你好 比尔博先生 来看看
Hello, Mr. Bilbo. Here.
摸摸我这些球薯 又好又脆 看看
Have a feel of me tubers. Nice and firm, they are.
- 刚从西区运来的  - 很好 瓦利沃特先生
- Just come in from West Farthing.  - Very impressive, Mr. Worrywort.
这个 我估计你没看到一个巫师藏在这附近吧?
Now, I don't suppose you've seen a Wizard lurking around these parts?
是个高个子
A tall fellow.
长长的 灰色胡子
Long, gray beard.
带着尖尖的帽子
Pointy hat.
没见过那样的
Can't say I have.
德瓦林 为您效劳
Dwalin, at your service.
嗯 呃...
Hm. Uh...
比尔博・巴金斯 也为您效劳
Bilbo Baggins, at yours.
我们...
Do we...
认识吗?
know each other?
不认识
No.
在哪 老弟?
Which way, laddie?
是在这下面吗?
Is it down here?
什么在...
Is what...
哪里下面?
down where?
晚餐
Supper.
他说这里有吃的 而且有很多
He said there'd be food and lots of it.
他... 他说? 谁说?
He... He said? Who said?
嗯
Mmm.
很好吃 这个 还有吗?
Very good, this. Any more?
什么? 哦 有 是
What? Oh, yes, yes.
呃
Ah.
请自便
Help yourself.
嗯 只是 呃 我没想到会有人来
Hmm. It's just that, um, I wasn't expecting company.
来客人了
That'll be the door.
巴林...
Balin...
为您效劳
at your service.
晚上好
Good evening.
是的 今晚很好
Yes. Yes, it is.
- 但恐怕一会儿要下雨  - 嗯?
- Though I think it might rain later.  - Hm?
我迟到了吗?
Am I late?
迟到什么?
Late for what?
喔
Oh!
哈 哈!
Ha, ha!
晚上好 兄弟
Evening, brother.
我发誓...
By my beard...
你比上次见面时更矮更胖了
you're shorter and wider than last we met.
胖了 没有矮
Wider, not shorter.
看上去依然神采奕奕
Sharp enough for both of us.
抱歉? 对不起 我不想打扰
Uh, excuse me? Sorry, I hate to interrupt.
但是 你们应该走错人家了吧
But the thing is, I'm not entirely sure you're in the right house.
- 你吃饭了么?  - 我不是不喜欢客人...
- Have you eaten?  - It's not that I don't like visitors...
我跟隔壁的...
I like visitors...
霍比特人一样好客
as much as the next Hobbit.
不过我还是喜欢已经认识的客人
But I do like to know them before they come visiting.
- 这是啥?  - 没见过
- What is this?  - I don't know.
- 我觉得是奶酪 变蓝了  - 那是发霉了
- I think it's cheese. Gone blue.  - It's riddled with mold.
是这样 我不认识你们俩 一点都不认识 我不想...
The thing is, I don't know either of you. Not in the slightest. I don't mean...
没礼貌 不过还是得说出来
to be blunt, but I had to speak my mind.
- 对不起  - 你认为...?
- I'm sorry.  - You think...?
原谅你了
Apology accepted.
- 啊  - 快 倒满 兄弟...
- Ah.  - Now, fill it up, brother...
别小气
don't stint.
- 你想撑死啊?  - 你想看吗 我还能再吃一遍
- You wanna get stuck in?  - I could eat again if you insist, brother.
- 菲力  - 还有奇力
- Fili.  - And Kili.
为您效劳
At your service.
你一定是巴金斯先生
You must be Mr. Boggins.
不是! 你们不能进来 你们走错了
Nope! You can't come in. You've come to the wrong house.
什么?
What?
- 取消了吗?  - 没人通知我们
- Has it been canceled?  - No one told us.
不 没有取消
No, nothing's been canceled.
那就好
That's a relief.
小心放置
Careful with these.
我刚磨过的
I just had them sharpened.
- 这地方不错  - 是啊
- It's nice, this place.  - Yeah.
- 你自己建的?  - 什么? 不 家族流传了很多年了
- Did you do it yourself?  - What? No, it's been in the family for years.
那是我妈妈的嫁妆箱 不要这样好吗?
That's my mother's glory box. Can you please not do that?
菲力 奇力 过来搭把手
Fili, Kili. Come on, give us a hand.
德瓦林先生 哈哈
Mr. Dwalin. Ha, ha.
把这个推到走廊去 不然就不能全进来了
Shove this in the hallway. Otherwise we'll never get everyone in.
"全进来"? 还有多少? 你要搬哪去?
"Everyone"? How many more are there? Where do you want this?
- 不行  - 太重了
- Oh, no.  - It's really heavy.
不许进来 家里没人!
No. No. There's nobody home!
找别人称兄道弟去吧
Go away and bother somebody else.
餐厅里的矮人多得装不下了
There's far too many Dwarves in my dining room as it is.
如果这是哪个榆木脑袋搞的恶作剧...
If this is some clot-head's idea of a joke...
我只能说...
I can only say it is in very...
太没品了
poor taste.
下去...
Get off...
你个大块头!
you big lump!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
抱歉 那是我的鸡肉 呃...
Excuse me, that's my chicken. Um...
别... 别碰... 那是我的酒 拜托!
If... If you don't... That's my wine. Excuse me!
他受伤了
He's got an injury.
你指他头上的斧子?
You mean the ax in his head?
死了? 不 只是砍在脑门上
Dead? No, only between his ears.
还能走路呢
His legs work fine.
把这些东西放回去
Put those back.
放回去
Put that back.
别拿果酱
Not the jam.
拜托 拜托
Excuse me. Excuse me.
稍微有点多了 对吧? 你有奶酪刀吗?
It's a tad excessive, isn't it? Have you got a cheese knife?
- "奶酪刀"? 他整块的吃  - 呃
- "Cheese knife"? He eats it by the block.  - Ugh.
不 那是蒙哥祖父的椅子... 不行 那个也是 拜托放回去
No, that's Grandpa Mungo's chair... No, so is that. Take it back, please.
- 我听不到你说什么  - 这是古董 不是用来坐的
- I cannot hear what you're saying.  - It's an antique. Not for sitting on.
那是书 不是杯托 地图也放下
That is a book, not a coaster. And put that map down.
- 抱歉 甘道夫先生?  - 怎么?
- Excuse me, Mr. Gandalf?  - Yes?
要来一杯甘菊茶吗?
May I tempt you with a cup of chamomile?
不 谢谢了 朵力 还是来杯红酒好了
Oh, no, thank you, Dori. A little red wine for me, I think.
哦! 小心
Whoop! Mind out.
呃 菲力 奇力 呃...
Uh, Fili, Kili. Uh...
欧因 葛罗因
Oin, Gloin.
德瓦林 巴林 毕佛 波佛 庞博...
Dwalin, Balin, Bifur, Bofur, Bombur...
- 朵力 诺力 欧力!  - 不 不许吃我的得奖作品 谢谢
- Dori, Nori. Ori!  - No. Not my prizewinners, thank you.
放手 谢谢
No, thank you.
嗯 说的很对 毕佛
Yes, you're quite right, Bifur.
好像还少了一个矮人
We appear to be one Dwarf short.
他只是迟到了 他去北方跟同族开会了 他会来的
He is late, is all. He traveled north to a meeting of our kin. He will come.
甘道夫先生? 您要的红酒来了
Mr. Gandalf? A little glass of red wine, as requested.
有一股水果的芳香
It's got a fruity bouquet.
哦 干杯
Oh. Cheers.
庞博在吃第二条羊腿了
Bombur's on his second leg of lamb already.
不可能 那么远肯定接不住
No chance. Not from that distance.
打赌?庞博...
Wanna bet? Bombur...
接着!
catch!
我来帮你
I'll help you with that.
哦 你这...
Oh, you great...
大饭桶
galumphing git!
谁还要麦芽酒? 给你
Who wants an ale? There you go.
伙计 这里
Over here, brother.
你得再喝一杯...
I said have another drink...
给你
Here you go.
数三声干杯!
Ale on the count of three!
一...
One...
- 二...  - 干杯!
- two...  - Up!
就知道你会这样!
I knew you had it in you!
抱歉 这是杯垫 不是抹布
Excuse me, that is a doily, not a dishcloth.
都破成这样了
But it's full of holes.
它就应该长这样 针织的
It's supposed to look like that. It's crochet.
如果你喜欢的话 编织也是很好玩的
And a wonderful game it is too, if you've got the balls for it.
这些矮人真讨厌!
Bebother and confusticate these Dwarves!
亲爱的比尔博 你这是怎么了?
My dear Bilbo, what on earth is the matter?
怎么了? 我家里一堆矮人
What's the matter? I'm surrounded by Dwarves.
他们来这干什么?
What are they doing here?
习惯了就会觉得他们是很欢乐的一群人了
Oh, they're quite a merry gathering once you get used to them.
我不想习惯他们
I don't want to get used to them.
瞧瞧我的厨房 地毯上踩的全是泥巴
Look at the state of my kitchen. There's mud trod into the carpet.
储藏室也被一扫而光
They've pillaged the pantry.
更别说他们在厕所干的事情了
I won't tell you what they've done in the bathroom.
下水道都坏了 真不知道他们来我家干什么!
They've destroyed the plumbing. I don't understand what they're doing in my house!
抱歉 打扰一下 这盘子该怎么处理?
Excuse me. I'm sorry to interrupt, but what should I do with my plate?
这儿 欧力 给我吧
Here you go, Ori. Give it to me.
放回来
Take that back.
拜托
Excuse me.
这是我母亲的...
That's my mother's...
西域陶瓷 已经有...
West Farthing pottery. It's over...
100多年历史了!
100 years old!
你们能...
And can you...
不这样么?
not do that?
刀子会变钝的
You'll blunt them.
听他说啥了吗 小子们?
Ooh. Do you hear that, lads?
他说...
He says...
我们会把刀弄钝
we'll blunt the knives.
# 刀子敲钝 叉子掰弯 #
# Blunt the knives, bend the forks #
# 瓶子打破 木塞烧了 #
# Smash the bottles and burn the corks #
# 杯子敲烂 盘子摔碎 #
# Chip the glasses and crack the plates #
# 气得比尔博・巴金斯火冒三丈 #
# That's what Bilbo Baggin hates#
# 衣服撕碎 满地油腻 #
# Cut the cloth, tread on the fat #
# 吃剩骨头 垫子上放 #
# Leave the bones on the bedroom mat #
# 牛奶打开 倒在地上 #
# Pour the milk on the pantry floor #
# 酒渍溅到 #
# Splash the wine #
# 每扇门上 #
# on every door #
# 陶瓷摔碎 扔碗里煮 #
# Dump the crocks in a boiling bowl #
# 拿个棍子 全部打碎 #
# Pound them up with a thumping pole #
# 完事之后 #
# When you're finished #
# 若还完整 #
# If they are whole #
# 全扔客厅 散落一地 #
# Send them down the hall to roll #
# 气得比尔博・巴金斯火冒三丈 #
# That's what Bilbo Baggins hates #
比尔博
Bilbo.
他来了
He is here.
你好 甘道夫
Gandalf.
我记得你说...
I thought you said...
这里很好找...
this place would be easy to find...
但我迷路了 两次
I lost my way, twice.
要不是门上有标记 我绝对找不到这儿
I wouldn't have found it at all had it not been for that mark on the door.
标记? 门上没有标记 一周前刚漆过
Mark? There's no mark on that door. It was painted a week ago.
有的 我标记上去的
There is a mark. I put it there myself.
比尔博・巴金斯 允许我向你介绍这些伙伴的领袖:
Bilbo Baggins, allow me to introduce the leader of our company:
索林・橡木盾
Thorin Oakenshield.
那么...
So...
你就是那个霍比特人
this is the Hobbit.
和我说说 巴金斯先生 以前打过仗吗?
Tell me, Mr. Baggins, have you done much fighting?
- 你说什么?  - 用斧子还是剑?
- Pardon me? Ax or sword?
喜欢用什么武器?
What's your weapon of choice?
呃 非要问的话 我对扔板栗颇有心得...
Well, I do have some skill at conkers, if you must know...
但这有什么联系吗?
but I fail to see why that's relevant.
如我所料
Thought as much.
比起飞贼 他更像个杂货商
He looks more like a grocer than a burglar.
伊瑞德隆会议...
What news...
传来什么消息? 他们都来了吗?
from the meeting in Ered Luin? Did they all come?
- 七个王国的使者都来了  - 全都来了!
- Aye. Envoys from all seven kingdoms.  - All of them!
铁丘陵的矮人怎么说?
And what did the Dwarves of the Iron Hills say?
戴因来吗?
Is Dain with us?
他们不愿意来
They will not come.
他们说这次探险...
They say this quest...
仅仅是我们自己的事
is ours and ours alone.
你们要去探险?
You're going on a quest?
比尔博 亲爱的伙计 再多点几盏灯吧
Bilbo, my dear fellow, let us have a little more light.
在遥远的东方...
Far to the east...
穿越无数的山脉河流...
over ranges and rivers...
跨过无尽的森林和荒漠...
beyond woodlands and wastelands...
有一座孤峰傲立着
lies a single, solitary peak.
"孤山"
"The Lonely Mountain."
没错 欧因读到过...
Aye, Oin has read...
预言的征兆 征兆显示时机已到
the portents, and the portents say it is time.
如预言所述...
Ravens have been seen...
渡鸦飞回山中
flying back to the mountain, as it was foretold.
"昔日的鸟儿回归...
"When the birds of yore return...
伊鲁柏之时...
to Erebor...
魔兽的统治...
the reign of the beast...
将会结束"
will end. "
- 什么魔兽?  - 指的是...
- Uh, what beast?  - That would be a reference...
恐惧之王史矛革...
to Smaug the Terrible...
我们时代...
chiefest and greatest...
最可怕的灾难
calamity of our age.
会飞的喷火者
Airborne fire-breather.
剃刀般尖锐的牙齿...
Teeth like razors...
肉钩一样的爪子
claws like meat hooks.
极度喜爱贵重金属
Fond of precious metals.
我知道龙长啥样
I know what a dragon is.
我才不怕 我准备好了
I'm not afraid. I'm up for it.
我要让他的菊花好好尝尝矮人钢铁的厉害!
I'll give him a taste of Dwarfish iron right up his jacksie!
好小子 欧力!
Good lad, Ori!
坐下
Sit down.
即使整支军队出动...
The task would be difficult...
任务也很艰巨...
with an army behind us...
何况我们只有13个人
but we number just 13.
而且其中还有歪瓜裂枣...
And not 13 of the best...
傻头傻脑的
nor brightest.
喂 你说谁傻瓜呢?
Hey, who are you calling dim?
不好意思 他刚说什么?
Sorry, what did he say?
我们虽然人少...
We may be few in number...
但我们是战士 所有人...
but we're fighters, all of us...
都会奋战到底
to the last Dwarf.
你们还忘了 我们有巫师结伴
And you forget, we have a Wizard in our company.
甘道夫可以杀掉上百条龙
Gandalf will have killed hundreds of dragons.
这个 我不敢说...
Oh, well, no. I wouldn't say...
- 那有多少?  - 什么?
- How many, then?  - What?
你杀过多少条龙?
How many dragons have you killed?
说啊
Go on.
给个数
Give us a number.
拜托 别吵了
Excuse me. Please.
如果我们能看见这些预兆...
If we have read these signs...
难道别的种族就看不出来吗?
do you not think others will have read them too?
谣言已经传开
Rumors have begun to spread.
那巨龙史矛革已经有60年无人见过
The dragon, Smaug, has not been seen for 60 years.
许多人都觊觎着东方那片土地 思索...
Eyes look east to the mountain, assessing...
徘徊 权衡利弊
wondering, weighing the risk.
或许我们的宝藏现在无人看守
Perhaps the vast wealth of our people now lies unprotected.
我们是坐视别人抢走我们的东西?
Do we sit back while others claim what is rightfully ours?
还是抓住机会...
Or do we seize this chance...
夺回伊鲁柏?
to take back Erebor?
可是 要塞的正门被堵死了
You forget, the Front Gate is sealed.
已经没有路...
There is no way...
可以进山了
into the mountain.
这可未必 亲爱的巴林
That, my dear Balin, is not entirely true.
你怎么会有这个?
How came you by this?
是你父亲...
It was given to me...
给我的
by your father.
索恩给我的
By Thrain.
要我保管
For safekeeping.
现在...
It is yours...
是你的了
now.
如果有钥匙...
If there is a key...
肯定就有门
there must be a door.
这些符语...
These runes...
暗示有个密门通向要塞大厅
speak of a hidden passage to the Lower Halls.
有别的方法进去
There's another way in.
能找到最好 但矮人的门关着的时候看不见
Well, if we can find it, but Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
位置就在这张地图上...
The answer lies hidden somewhere in this map...
但是我不知道如何找到它
and I do not have the skill to find it.
但是中土世界有人可以
But there are others in Middle-earth who can.
我想的计划需要做的非常隐蔽...
The task I have in mind will require a great deal of stealth...
并且需要巨大的勇气
and no small amount of courage.
如果我们够细心够机灵 我相信是可以做到的
But if we are careful and clever, I believe that it can be done.
所以我们需要一个飞贼
That's why we need a burglar.
要一个本领高强的飞贼 最好是专家
Hmm. And a good one too. An expert, I'd imagine.
你是吗?
And are you?
我是什么?
Am I what?
他说他就是一个专家
He said he's an expert.
我? 不不 我不是飞贼 我这辈子从未偷过东西
Me? No. No, no, no. I'm not a burglar. I've never stolen a thing in my life.
我也同意巴金斯先生
Well, I'm afraid I have to agree with Mr. Baggins.
他绝对不是当飞贼的料
He's hardly burglar material.
不是
Nope.
是啊 既不会战斗也不会防御的软弱之人无法在野外生存
Aye, the Wild is no place for gentle folk who can neither fight nor fend for themselves.
他也就一般
He's just fine.
够了!
Enough!
我说比尔博・巴金斯是...
If I say Bilbo Baggins...
飞贼 那他...
is a burglar, then a burglar...
就是
he is.
霍比特人的脚步轻盈...
Hobbits are light on their feet...
如果他们想 大多数人都注意不到他们
In fact, they can pass unseen by most, if they choose.
虽然龙对于矮人气味十分熟悉...
And, while the dragon is accustomed to the smell of Dwarf...
但是霍比特人的气息 它就完全不了解...
the scent of a Hobbit is all but unknown to him...
这会给我们带来很大优势
which gives us a distinct advantage.
你让我寻找第14名成员
You asked me to find the 14th member of this
我推荐巴金斯先生
company and I have chosen Mr. Baggins.
他还是很能干的 别被外表迷惑了
There's a lot more to him than appearances suggest.
他所能做的 完全超乎你们得想象
And he's got a great deal more to offer than any of you know.
他自己也不知道
Including himself.
在这点上 你得相信我
You must trust me on this.
好吧
Very well.
- 就按你的来做  - 不 不
- We will do it your way.  - No, no.
- 把合同给他  - 算我们一个
- Give him the contract.  - We're in. We're off.
这是惯例条款
It's just the usual.
包括总体支出...
Summary of out-of-pocket expenses...
所需时间 报酬...
time required, remuneration...
葬礼安排 等等
funeral arrangements, so forth.
葬礼安排?
Funeral arrangements?
我可不能保证他小命安全
I cannot guarantee his safety.
了解
Understood.
未来我也不会照顾他
Nor will I be responsible for his fate.
同意
Agreed.
"条款: 事成付款
"Terms: Cash on
报酬将达到并不超过总收益的十四分之一 如果有收益"
delivery, up to but not exceeding one-fourteenth of total profit, if any."
很公平
Hmm. Seems fair.
"本队将不对成员未来所受的各种伤负责...
"Present company shall not be liable for injuries inflicted by...
这些伤害包括但不局限于撕裂伤...
or sustained as a consequence thereof, including, but not limited to lacerations...
内脏伤..."
evisceration..."
火葬?
Incineration?
对 那龙也许眨眼间就把你的血肉全部烧了
Aye. He'll melt the flesh off your bones in the blink of an eye.
- 你没事吧?  - 嗯? 我很好
- You all right, laddie?  - Huh? Yeah.
头有点晕
Feel a bit faint.
- 想象一下会飞的火炉  - 新鲜空气
- Think furnace with wings.  - Air.
我需要缓口气
I need air.
炽烈的亮光 灼烧的疼痛 然后噗的一下
Flash of light, searing pain, then poof.
你就成了一堆炭灰了
You're nothing more than a pile of ash.
不好
Nope.
你真会帮倒忙 波佛
Oh, very helpful, Bofur.
我没事的 让我安静的待会就行了
I'll be all right. Just let me sit quietly for a moment.
你太沉溺于这种安逸的生活了
You've been sitting quietly for far too long.
你怎么对那些杯垫和你老妈的碟子...
Tell me, when did doilies and your mother's dishes...
看得如此重要?
become so important to you?
我记忆中的那个小霍比特人总是
I remember a young Hobbit who was always
在林子间寻找精灵们
running off in search of Elves in the woods.
总是玩到很晚回家...
Who would stay out late, come home after dark...
全身都是泥巴 树枝 还有萤火虫
trailing mud and twigs and fireflies.
那个年轻的霍比特人 总是想要...
A young Hobbit who would have liked nothing better...
探索夏尔外面的世界
than to find out what was beyond the borders of the Shire.
世界可不是一本书或是一张地图
The world is not in your books and maps.
它在屋外
It's out there.
我不能就这样无声无息地和你们走
I can't just go running off into the blue.
我是住在袋底洞的巴金斯
I am a Baggins of Bag-end.
但你也是图克家族的
You are also a Took.
你知道吗 你的曾曾曾曾伯父 吼牛・图克...
Did you know that your great-great-great-great-uncle Bullroarer Took...
体型大得能够骑一匹马吗?
was so large, he could ride a real horse?
- 知道  - 当然 他可以
- Yes.  - Yes, well, he could.
绿原之战中 他冲向哥布林大军
In the Battle of Green Fields, he charged the Goblin ranks.
他的力量之大 用棒子生生把敌方国王脑袋敲下来...
He swung his club so hard, it knocked the Goblin king's head clean off...
滚了一百多码才掉到一个兔子窝里
and it sailed 100 yards through the air and went down a rabbit hole.
他们赢得了战役
And thus, the battle was won.
从那以后 有人因此发明了高尔夫(哥布林国王名叫高尔夫裘)
And the game of golf invented at the same time.
我知道你是乱编的
I do believe you made that up.
所有精彩的故事都需要润润色嘛
Well, all good stories deserve embellishment.
如果你回来了 那你也有自己的传奇故事了
You'll have a tale or two to tell of your own when you come back.
你能保证我能安全回来?
Can you promise that I will come back?
不能
No.
如果你能回得来...
And if you do...
你绝对不会和现在一样
you will not be the same.
我也同意
That's what I thought.
不好意思 甘道夫 我不能签这个
Sorry, Gandalf, I can't sign this.
你找错霍比特人了
You've got the wrong Hobbit.
我们的飞贼似乎不干了
It appears we have lost our burglar.
也许这样也好
Probably for the best.
事事总不能如意啊
The odds were always against us.
说到底 我们是什么?
After all, what are we?
商人 矿工...
Merchants, miners...
铁匠 做玩具的
tinkers, toy-makers.
看起来不太像是一群英雄们
Heh, heh. Hardly the stuff of legend.
我们中间还是有战士的
There are a few warriors amongst us.
残兵败将
Old warriors.
比起铁丘陵的矮人军队
I would take each and every one of these Dwarves...
我宁可有这些人的追随
over an army from the Iron Hills.
因为在我号召时他们一定能回应
For when I called upon them, they answered.
忠诚 荣耀...
Loyalty, honor...
热诚
a willing heart.
我觉得这些就够了
I can ask no more than that.
你不必亲自去
You don't have to do this.
你可以选择不去
You have a choice.
我们族人拥戴你 愿意受你领导
You've done honorably by our people.
是你在蓝山开辟新的居住地
You have built a new life for us in the Blue Mountains.
过着和平富裕的生活
A life of peace and plenty.
我觉得这一切比伊鲁柏的金子更宝贵
A life that is worth more than all the gold in Erebor.
从我的爷爷传到我父亲 现在到我了
From my grandfather to my father, this has come to me.
他们无时无刻都在想着矮人能重夺自己的故乡
They dreamt of the day when the Dwarves of Erebor would reclaim their homeland.
没有其他选择 巴林
There is no choice, Balin.
我别无选择
Not for me.
那么 我们将与你同生共死
Then we are with you, laddie.
我们会成功的
We will see it done.
# 登上远山冰寒之巅 #
# Far over the misty mountains cold #
# 深入地牢深渊之底 #
# To dungeons deep #
# 探索古老洞窟之中 #
# And caverns old #
# 在太阳升起之前 #
# We must away #
# 我们必须整装出发 #
# 'Ere break of day #
# 去追寻那遗落之财 #
# To find our long-forgotten gold #
# 高处的松树在低吼 #
# The pines were roaring on the height #
# 夜晚的寒风在呼啸 #
# The winds were moaning in the night #
# 希望之火 传播不息 #
# The fire was red, it flaming spread #
# 光明从这火中而来 #
# The trees like torches blazed with light #
早啊?
Hello?
好样的
Yes.
不错
比尔博先生 你这是去哪儿?
Here, Mr. Bilbo, where are you off to?
- 不能停下说 我已经迟到了!  - 什么迟到?
- Can't stop, I'm already late!  - Late for what?
我要去冒险!
I'm going on an adventure!
我说过的 我说过吗? 这一趟来得不值啊
I said it. Didn't I say it? Coming here was a waste of time.
你说的没错
That's true enough.
这主意太荒唐了 霍比特人? 半身人(通用语中对霍比特人的称呼)?
Ridiculous notion. Use a Hobbit? A Halfling?
等等!
Wait!
等下我!
我签名了
I signed it.
给
Here.
很好 一切都按程序填写
Everything appears to be in order.
欢迎 巴金斯大师...
Welcome, Master Baggins...
欢迎加入索林・橡木盾小队
to the company of Thorin Oakenshield.
给他一匹马崽子
Give him a pony.
哦 不用这么麻烦了
No, no, that won't be necessary.
谢了 我自信我能赶上你们步伐
Thank you. I'm sure I can keep up on foot.
我经常出去徒步旅游的 知道吗?
I've done my fair share of walking holidays, you know?
有一次还跑到蛙村去了
Even got as far as Frogmorton once.
快点 诺力 给钱
Come on, Nori. Pay up.
- 还有一袋  - 谢了 小子
- One more.  - Thanks, lad.
这是干嘛?
What's that about?
哦 他们在打赌 赌你会不会回心转意
Oh, they took wagers on whether or not you'd turn up.
大多数人赌你不会
Most of them bet that you wouldn't.
你觉得呢?
And what did you think?
我的好朋友 我从未怀疑过你
My dear fellow, I never doubted you for a second.
这马毛让我过敏了
It's horse hair. Having a reaction.
不不 等下
No, wait, wait, stop.
停下! 我们得回头
Stop! We have to turn around.
到底怎么啦?
What on earth is the matter?
- 我忘记带我的手帕了  - 给你
- I forgot my handkerchief.  - Here.
用这个
Use this.
继续行进
Move on.
你得习惯不带手帕的生活...
You'll have to manage without pocket handkerchiefs...
还有很多其他的事情 比尔博・巴金斯...
and a good many other things, Bilbo Baggins...
直到这趟旅程结束
before we reach our journey's end.
你在夏尔的丘陵与小河边长大
You were born to the rolling hills and little rivers of the Shire.
但如今家园已在身后
But home is now behind you.
世界尽在眼前
The world is ahead.
嗨 姑娘 真是个好姑娘!
Hello, girl. Who's a good girl?
这是我俩的小秘密 桃金娘
It's our little secret, Myrtle.
谁也不许告诉 嘘 嘘
You must tell no one. Shh, shh.
那是什么?
What was that?
是半兽人
Orcs.
半兽人?
Orcs?
是些嗜杀成性的家伙 外头起码有几十个
Throat-cutters. There'll be dozens of them out there.
在孤土到处可见它们的身影(孤土西起蓝山 东至迷雾山脉)
The lone-lands are crawling with them.
他们总在凌晨时分 人们熟睡时动手
They strike in the wee small hours when everyone's asleep.
干脆利落 人们来不及尖叫 就已血流成河
Quick and quiet, no screams. Just lots of blood.
你们以为这些很好玩?
You think that's funny?
你们以为被半兽人夜袭是个玩笑?
You think a night raid by Orcs is a joke?
我们不是这个意思
We didn't mean anything by it.
是啊 你们不是这个意思
No, you didn't.
你们对这世界根本一无所知
You know nothing of the world.
别介意 小家伙
Don't mind him, laddie.
索林比任何人都更有理由痛恨半兽人
Thorin has more cause than most to hate Orcs.
在恶龙占领孤山后...
After the dragon took the Lonely Mountain...
国王索尔曾试图收复古老的矮人王国 摩瑞亚
King Thror tried to reclaim the ancient Dwarf kingdom of Moria.
但敌人早已捷足先登
But our enemy had got there first.
摩瑞亚被半兽人军团占领...
Moria had been taken by legions of Orcs...
领头的是它们族群中最邪恶的家伙
led by the most vile of all their race:
毁灭者阿索格
Azog the Defiler.
这个身形巨大的刚达巴半兽人
The giant Gundabad Orc...
曾发誓要杀尽杜林一族
had sworn to wipe out the line of Durin.
他一出手...
He began...
就砍下了国王的脑袋
by beheading the king.
不!
No!
索林的父亲索恩悲伤得几乎发狂
Thrain, Thorin's father, was driven mad by grief.
他失踪了 也许被俘 也许被杀...
He went missing. Taken prisoner or killed...
我们无从知晓
We did not know.
我们失去了首领
We were leaderless.
失败与死亡...
Defeat and death...
正步步紧逼
were upon us.
就在那时我看到了他
That is when I saw him.
一位年轻的矮人王子...
A young Dwarf prince...
力战苍白半兽人
facing down the pale Orc.
他孤身与强敌血战
He stood alone against this terrible foe.
他的盔甲碎了...
His armor rent...
只能挥舞着一截橡木当盾牌
wielding nothing but an oaken branch as a shield.
那一天 毁灭者阿索格明白了...
Azog the Defiler learned that day...
杜林族系绝不会轻易瓦解
that the line of Durin would not be so easily broken.
为荣誉
给我杀!
我们集结了军力
Our forces rallied...
击退了半兽人
and drove the Orcs back.
我们的敌人...
And our enemy...
被打败了
had been defeated.
但那一晚既没有庆宴...
But there was no feast...
也没有歌声...
nor song that night...
因为我们的伤亡太过惨重
for our dead were beyond the count of grief.
只有极少数得以存活
We few had survived.
于是我告诉自己...
And I thought to myself then...
还有这样一个人值得我去追随
there is one who I could follow.
还有这样一个人...
There is one...
我愿视为王
I could call king.
那苍白半兽人呢?
And the pale Orc?
他后来怎么样了?
What happened to him?
他溜回了起兵的那个洞里
He slunk back into the hole whence he came.
早就因伤势过重死了
That filth died of his wounds long ago.
向大王汇报...
我们找到了该死的矮人
喂 甘道夫先生 这水漫金山的你就不能想想办法吗?
Here, Mr. Gandalf, can't you do something about this deluge?
这是在下雨 矮人大人...
It is raining, Master Dwarf...
想止住雨的唯一办法就是等雨自己停下来
and it will continue to rain until the rain is done.
如果你想改变这世界上的天气 那恐怕得找别的巫师了
If you wish to change the weather of the world, you should find yourself another Wizard.
- 有别的吗?  - 别的什么?
- Are there any?  - What?
- 别的巫师  - 像我们这样的人有五个
- Other Wizards.  - There are five of us.
其中最位高权重的是白袍萨鲁曼
The greatest of our order is Saruman the White.
接下来是两位蓝袍巫师...
Then there are the two Blue Wizards...
不过我已经忘了他们的名字了
Do you know, I've quite forgotten their names.
那第五个呢?
And who is the fifth?
是褐袍瑞达加斯特
Well, that would be Radagast the Brown.
他是个厉害的巫师吗? 还是和你差不多的?
Is he a great Wizard? Or is he more like you?
我想他自有他厉害的地方
I think he's a very great Wizard, in his own way.
他心地温和 偏爱与动物为伴
He's a gentle soul who prefers the company of animals to others.
始终盯防着东部的...
He keeps a watchful eye over the vast forest lands...
广阔森林地带 这是件好事
to the east. And a good thing too.
因为邪恶势力总会试图在世上寻找立足之地
For always evil will look to find a foothold in this world.
不妙 大事不妙了
Not good. Not good at all.
唷
Eww.
哦 不 塞巴斯蒂安
Oh, no. Sebastian.
我的天哪
Good gracious.
快点
Come on.
退后! 给它点新鲜空气 拜托了
Move back! Give him some air, for goodness sake.
来 给
There. There.
我不明白为什么不起作用
I don't understand why it's not working.
这又不是巫术
It's not as if it's witchcraft.
巫术
Witchcraft.
哦 但它确实是巫术
Oh, but it is.
一种邪恶 强大的魔法
A dark and powerful magic.
让这动物免于诅咒
Lerya laman naiquentallo.
现在聆听我的声音
Si a hlare omaquettar.
让其重新焕发生机
Na coilerya en-vinyanta.
现在聆听我的声音
Si a hlare omaquettar.
让其重新焕发生机
Na coilerya en-vinyanta.
那些肮脏的生物究竟是从哪里来的?
Where on this good earth did those foul creatures come from?
古要塞?
The old fortress?
带我去
Show me.
我们今晚在这里扎营
We'll camp here for the night.
菲力 奇力 照看好马儿 和它们待在一块
Fili, Kili, look after the ponies. Make sure you stay with them.
这里以前住着一户农民
A farmer and his family used to live here.
- 欧因 葛罗因 生火  - 是
- Oin, Gloin. Get a fire going.  - Aye.
好的
Right you are.
我觉得还是继续前进比较明智
I think it would be wiser to move on.
我们可以前往幽谷
We could make for the Hidden Valley.
我已经告诉你了...
I have told you already...
我不会靠近那地方
I will not go near that place.
为什么? 精灵可以提供帮助
Why not? The Elves could help us.
我们能补充食物 休养生息 听取建议
We could get food, rest, advice.
我不需要精灵的建议
I do not need their advice.
我们还有一张地图看不懂 爱隆能帮助我们
We have a map that we cannot read. Lord Elrond could help us.
帮助?
Help?
恶龙袭击伊鲁柏的时候
A dragon attacks Erebor.
精灵提供帮助了吗?
What help came from the Elves?
半兽人扫荡摩瑞亚...
Orcs plunder Moria...
亵渎圣殿的时候
desecrate our sacred halls.
精灵们只是袖手旁观
The Elves looked on and did nothing.
而你却要我去找那些背叛我祖父的人
And you ask me to seek out the very people who betrayed my grandfather.
那些背叛我父亲的人
Who betrayed my father.
但你不是他们
You are neither of them.
我给你地图和钥匙 不是为了让你执着于往事
I did not give you that map and key for you to hold onto the past.
那本来就是属于我的
I did not know that they were yours to keep.
没事吧? 甘道夫你要去哪?
Everything all right? Gandalf, where are you going?
去找这里唯一一个有理智的人
To seek the company of the only one around here who's got any sense.
- 是谁?  - 我自己 巴金斯先生
- And who's that?  - Myself, Mr. Baggins.
我今天已经受够了矮人了
I've had enough of Dwarves for one day.
快点 庞博 我们都饿了
Come on, Bombur, we're hungry.
他会回来吗?
Is he coming back?
他已经离开很久了
He's been a long time.
- 谁?  - 甘道夫
- Who?  - Gandalf.
他是个巫师 知道自己在做什么
He's a Wizard. He does as he chooses.
拿着 帮个忙 把这个给小伙子们送去
Here, do us a favor. Take this to the lads.
住手 你已经吃得够多了
Stop it. You've had plenty.
饭做得不错啊 庞博 我还吃过更糟的
Aye, it's not a bad stew, Bombur. I've had worse.
- 本来可以让朵力做的  - 哈哈哈
- Dori could've cooked it.  - Ha-ha-ha.
太好笑了
Hilarious.
怎么了?
What's the matter?
- 我们本应该看着马的  - 但我们遇到了些小问题
- We're supposed to be looking after the ponies.  - Only we've encountered a slight problem.
原本有16匹马
We had 16.
现在只有14匹了
Now there's 14.
黛西和伯格不见了
Daisy and Bungo are missing.
哦 那可不妙 哈 哈
Well, that's not good. Ha, ha.
那可糟透了 要去告诉索林吗?
And that is not good at all. Shouldn't we tell Thorin?
呃 不要 别让他担心
Uh, no. Let's not worry him.
身为队伍的正式飞贼 我们觉得你也许愿意去调查一下
As our official burglar, we thought you might like to look into it.
这个 呃...
Well, uh...
- 瞧 树像是被什么大家伙连根拔起的  - 我们也是这么想的
- Look, something big uprooted these trees.  - That was our thinking.
应该是某种巨大且危险的东西
It's something very big and possibly quite dangerous.
嘿
Hey.
那里有光亮
There's a light.
过来
Over here.
蹲下
Stay down.
那是什么?
What is it?
食人妖
Trolls.
哦
Oh.
他又抓走了桃金娘和薄荷
He's got Myrtle and Minty.
我想它们会被吃掉的 我们得采取行动
I think they're gonna eat them. We have to do something.
没错 你快上吧
Yes, you should.
食人妖脑袋又笨 动作又慢 你这么小 他们根本看不到你
Mountain Trolls are slow and stupid, and you're so small, they'll never see you.
绝对安全 我们会跟在你身后的
It's perfectly safe. We'll be behind you.
如果遇到麻烦 就学谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 棕色猫头鹰叫一声
If you run into trouble, hoot twice like a barn owl and once like a brown owl.
谷仓猫头鹰叫两声 不对 棕色猫头鹰叫两... 谷仓...
Twice like a barn owl. No, twice like a brown... Once like a...
叫... 你们确定这是个好主意吗?
Like a... Are you sure this is a good idea?
昨天吃羊肉 今天吃羊肉...
Mutton yesterday, mutton today...
天哪 不会明天也吃羊肉吧
and, blimey, if it don't look like mutton again tomorrow.
别发牢骚了
Quit your griping.
这不是羊 这是新鲜的马肉
These ain't sheep. These is fresh nags.
哦! 我不喜欢马 从来没喜欢过 它们身上连肥肉都没有
Oh! I don't like horse. I never have. Not enough fat on them.
总比干巴巴的老农夫好吧
Well, it's better than leathery old farmer.
他简直是皮包骨头 到现在我牙缝里还有呢
All skin and bone, he was. I'm still picking bits of him out of me teeth.
真棒 瞧你干的好事 鼻涕进锅里了
Well, that's lovely, that is. A floater.
没准能添点味儿
Might improve the flavor.
啊 这儿还有呢
Ah. There's more where that came from.
- 哦 不 不准这样!  - 噢!
- Oh, no, you don't!  - Ow!
坐下!
Sit down!
希望你能把这些马的内脏去掉
Well, I hope you're gonna gut these nags.
我不喜欢吃内脏
I don't like the stinky parts.
- 噢!  - 我说了 坐下
- Ow!  - I said sit down.
我饿死了!
I'm starving!
今晚到底吃不吃马肉了?
Now, are we having horse tonight or what?
闭上你的臭嘴 我给什么你就吃什么
Shut your cakehole. You'll eat what I give you.
怎么让他当厨师的? 所有东西尝起来都是一个味儿
How come he's the cook? Everything tastes the same.
所有东西吃着都像鸡肉
Everything tastes like chicken.
除了鸡肉不像
Except the chicken.
鸡肉倒像是鱼!
What tastes like fish!
我刚说过 你们应该心存感激
I'm just saying, a little appreciation would be nice.
哦 "谢谢你 伯特 做得真棒 伯特"
Oh. "Thank you very much, Bert. Lovely stew, Bert."
- 这有什么难的?  - 嘘 嘘
- How hard is that?  - Shh. Shh, shh. Shh.
只需要再撒些松鼠粪
Just needs a sprinkle of squirrel dung.
嘿 那是我的酒
Here, that's my grog.
抱歉 噢!
Sorry. Ow!
哦 味道正好 不错
Ooh. That is beautifully balanced, that is.
把你嘴巴凑过来接住 嗯?
Wrap your laughing gear around that, eh?
不错吧?
Good, isn't it?
所以要我来当厨师
That's why I'm the cook.
哦 我肚子都叫了 我需要捞点东西吃
Oh, my guts are grumbling. I got to snaffle something.
- 肉 我要肉  - 啊! 啊!
- Flesh, I need flesh.  - Ah! Ah!
天哪!
Blimey!
伯特 伯特! 看我鼻子里喷出了什么
Bert. Bert! Look what's come out of me hooter.
它有手有脚 什么都有
It's got arms and legs and everything.
这是什么东西?
What is it?
我不知道 但我不喜欢它扭来扭去的样子
I don't know. But I don't like the way it wriggles around.
你是什么东西? 特大号松鼠吗?
What are you, then? An oversized squirrel?
我是个飞... 呃 霍比特人
I'm a burglar... Uh, Hobbit.
一个飞蛾霍比特人?
A burglar Hobbit?
我们能煮了他吗?
Can we cook him?
可以试试
We can try.
他还不够我咬一大口的
He wouldn't make more than a mouthful.
尽管不是皮包骨头
Not when he's skinned and boned.
也许附近还有更多的飞蛾霍比特人
Perhaps there's more burglar Hobbits around these parts.
说不定够做个派
Might be enough for a pie.
- 抓住他!  - 他动作太快了
- Grab him!  - He's too quick.
好吧 快过来 你这小东...
Right. Come here, you little...
抓住你了
Gotcha.
你还有其他小同伴躲在不该躲的地方吗?
Are there any more of you little fellas hiding where you shouldn't?
没有
No.
他在撒谎
He's lying.
- 不 我没有!  - 把他悬到火上烤
- No, I'm not!  - Hold his toes over the fire.
让他尖叫!
Make him squeal!
把他放下!
Drop him!
你说什么?
You what?
我说...
I said...
把他放下
drop him.
拿袋子来! 把他们用麻袋套上!
Get the sacks! Stick them in the sacks!
噢!
Ow!
快点! 起来!
Come on! Get up!
- 比尔博!  - 不要!
- Bilbo!  - Don't!
放下武器...
Lay down your arms...
不然我们就撕了他
or we'll rip his off.
哦! 烫死了 烫死了 烫死了!
Oh! That's hot, that's hot, that's hot!
别费劲煮他们了
Don't bother cooking them.
我们直接坐上去 把他们压成肉酱吧
Let's just sit on them and squash them into jelly.
应该先这样爆炒再煎烤 最后撒些鼠尾草
They should be sauteed and grilled with a sprinkle of sage.
这真的有必要吗?
Is this really necessary?
听起来确实不错
That does sound quite nice.
- 松开我 先生  - 去吃和你个子一样大的东西吧
- Untie me, mister.  - Eat someone your own size.
别介意调料了
Never mind the seasoning.
我们没有一整晚的时间
We ain't got all night.
黎明不远了 我们动作快点
Dawn ain't far away. Let's get a move on.
我可不想被变成石头
I don't fancy being turned to stone.
等等!
Wait!
你们犯了个大错
You are making a terrible mistake.
你没法和他们讲道理 他们是白痴!
You can't reason with them. They're half-wits!
白痴? 那我们成什么了?
Half-wits? What does that make us?
我指的是调料的事
I meant with the seasoning.
调料怎么了?
What about the seasoning?
你闻过他们的味道了么?
Well, have you smelt them?
想把他们烤熟装盘 你就得用比鼠尾草味道更重的调料
You're gonna need something stronger than sage before you plate this lot up.
- 叛徒!  - 你懂怎么煮矮人?
- Traitor!  - What do you know about cooking Dwarf?
闭嘴
Shut up.
让 小格灰灰霍比特人来说
Let the flurgaburburhobbit talk.
煮矮人的秘诀就在于...
The secret to cooking Dwarf is...
- 嗯? 说吧 告诉我们秘诀  - 呃 就是...
- Yes? Come on. Tell us the secret.  - It's, uh...
我正准备说呢 秘诀就是...
Yes, I'm telling you. The secret is...
先剥皮
to skin them first.
什么? 剥我们的皮?
What? Skin us?
汤姆 给我拿切片刀来
Tom, get me filleting knife.
我要剥了你的皮! 你这小...
I'll skin you, you little...!
我不会忘记这件事的 我绝不会忘记
I won't forget that. I won't forget it.
都是废话
What a load of rubbish.
我吃过好多带皮的
I've eaten plenty with their skins on.
一口吞下 连靴子也吃下去
Scarf them, I say, boots and all.
他说的对
He's right.
吃些活矮人也没关系
Nothing wrong with a bit of raw Dwarf.
美味又松脆
Nice and crunchy.
不 别挑那个 他被感染了
Oh, not that one. He's infected.
- 嗯?  - 你说什么?
- Huh?  - You what?
没错 他肠道里有虫子
Yeah, he's got worms in his tubes.
- 呕!  - 啊!
- Eww!  - Aah!
事实上 他们都被感染了 他们体内长满了寄生虫
In fact, they all have. They're infested with parasites.
那真是太可怕了 我可不会冒这种险 绝对不会
It's a terrible business. I wouldn't risk it. I really wouldn't.
寄生虫? 他说了 "寄生虫" ?
Parasites? Did he say "parasites"?
我们没有寄生虫 你才有寄生虫呢!
We don't have parasites. You have parasites!
你在说什么呢 小伙子?
What are you talking about, laddie?
我的寄生虫和手臂一样粗
I've got parasites as big as my arm.
我的寄生虫最大了 超大号寄生虫
Mine are the biggest parasites. I've got huge parasites.
- 我们身上到处都是  - 没错 我全身都是
- We're riddled.  - Yes, I'm riddled.
是的 我们糟透了
Yes, we are, badly.
那么你要我们怎么办?
What would you have us do, then?
放他们走?
Let them all go?
- 这个...  - 你以为我不知道你想干什么?
- Well...  - You think I don't know what you're up to?
这只小耗子把我们当傻子耍呢
This little ferret is taking us for fools.
- 耗子?  - 傻子?
- Ferret?  - Fools?
曙光将把你们全部消灭
The dawn will take you all.
- 那是谁?  - 不知道
- Who's that?  - No idea.
我们能把他也吃了吗?
Can we eat him too?
把你的脚从我背上拿开
Get your foot out of my back.
啊
Ah.
容我问一句 你之前去哪里了?
Where did you go to, if I may ask?
去前面看看
To look ahead.
- 你为什么又回来了?  - 看看后面
- What brought you back?  - Looking behind.
真糟糕
Nasty business.
幸好 大家都没事
Still, they're all in one piece.
你的飞贼可没什么功劳
No thanks to your burglar.
他给你们争取了时间
He had the nous to play for time.
你们都没有意识到这点
None of the rest of you thought of that.
这些食人妖一定都是从伊顿荒原来的
They must have come down from the Ettenmoors.
从什么时候开始 他们会往南走得这么远?
Since when do Mountain Trolls venture this far south?
哦 没多久
Ooh. Not for an age.
就在黑暗势力统治这片土地之后
Not since a darker power ruled these lands.
他们不能在白天活动
They could not have moved in daylight.
这附近一定会有个洞穴
There must be a cave nearby.
哦 这股臭味是哪来的?
Oh, what's that stench?
这里是食人妖的巢穴
It's a Troll-hoard.
小心你们摸到的东西
Be careful what you touch.
把财宝随意扔放 好像太可惜了
Seems a shame just to leave it lying around.
- 谁都可以拿走  - 同意
- Anyone could take it.  - Agreed.
- 诺力  - 干什么?
- Nori.  - Yeah?
拿把铲子来
Get a shovel.
这些剑不是食人妖做的
These swords were not made by any Troll.
也不是人类铁匠做的
Nor were they made by any smith among men.
这些是第一纪的高等精灵...
These were forged in Gondolin...
在贡多林锻造的
by the High Elves of the First Age.
没有比这更锋利的刀刃了
You could not wish for a finer blade.
- 把它埋起来  - 太好了
- Set it down.  - That's good.
好了 继续 快点
All right, come on. Quick.
我们也存点长期储蓄
We're making a long-term deposit.
我们快离开这个臭烘烘的地方吧
Let's get out of this foul place.
走吧 我们走
Come on, let's go.
跟上 波佛 葛罗因 诺力
Bofur, Gloin, Nori.
- 比尔博  - 嗯?
- Bilbo.  - Hmm?
给你
Here.
这个尺寸正适合你
This is about your size.
我不能接受它
I can't take this.
这把剑是精灵制作的...
The blade is of Elvish make...
也就是说当半兽人或哥布林靠近的时候 它会发出蓝色的光
which means it will glow blue when Orcs or Goblins are nearby.
我这辈子都没用过剑
I have never used a sword in my life.
我希望你永远用不上它
And I hope you never have to.
但是如果你用到了 要记住
But if you do, remember this:
真正的勇气 不是体现在杀戮的时候...
True courage is about knowing not when to take a life...
而是宽恕的时候
but when to spare one.
有什么东西过来了!
Something's coming!
- 甘道夫  - 聚在一起!
- Gandalf.  - Stay together!
快点! 拿上武器!
Hurry now! Arm yourselves!
小偷! 大火! 谋杀!
Thieves! Fire! Murder!
瑞达加斯特
Radagast.
这是褐袍瑞达加斯特
It's Radagast the Brown.
那么...
Well...
你来这里到底要干什么?
What on earth are you doing here?
我在找你 甘道夫
I was looking for you, Gandalf.
出事了
Something's wrong.
出大事了
Something's terribly wrong.
怎么了?
Yes?
哦
Oh.
稍等一下
Just give me a minute.
哦 我有件事想说 但是我给忘了
Oh. I had a thought and now I've lost it.
它就在...
It was right there...
我的舌尖上
on the tip of my tongue.
哦
Oh.
它根本不是一件事
It's not a thought at all.
它是一只笨笨的...
It's a silly old...
老竹节虫
stick insect.
巨绿森林生病了 甘道夫
The Greenwood is sick, Gandalf.
黑暗已经将它笼罩
A darkness has fallen over it.
万物都不再生长
Nothing grows anymore.
至少 美好的东西都不再生长
At least, nothing good.
空气中弥漫着浑浊的腐臭
The air is foul with decay.
更糟糕的是蛛网
But worse are the webs.
蛛网? 什么意思?
Webs? What do you mean?
蜘蛛 甘道夫
Spiders, Gandalf.
巨型的蜘蛛
Giant ones.
我肯定是昂哥立安的后代 否则我就不是个巫师
Some kind of spawn of Ungoliant, or I am not a Wizard.
我沿着它们的踪迹
I followed their trail.
追踪到它们来自多尔戈多
They came from Dol Guldur.
啊?
Huh?
来自多尔戈多?
Dol Guldur?
但是那座古老的堡垒已经被废弃了
But the old fortress is abandoned.
不 甘道夫
No, Gandalf.
那里有人
It's not.
一股黑暗势力盘踞在那里...
A dark power dwells in there...
那是我从未感受过的...
Such as I have never...
黑暗
felt before.
那是远古魔影
It is The Shadow of an ancient horror.
它可以召唤...
One that can summon the spirits...
亡者之灵
of the dead.
我看到他了 甘道夫
I saw him, Gandalf.
从黑暗中...
From out of the darkness...
走出来的是...
a Necromancer...
一位
has come.
死灵法师
Radagast.
快! 快! 快点! 快点!
Quick! Quick, quick! Quick, quick!
等等我!
Wait for me!
对不起
Sorry.
来一口老托比吧
Try a little Old Toby.
它能帮你放松下来
It'll help settle your nerves.
吐出来
And out.
现在好好想想...
Now...
你确定那是死灵法师吗?
a Necromancer. Are you sure?
那可不是...
That is not...
来自我们这个世界的东西
from the world of the living.
那是狼吗? 这附近有狼吗?
Was that a wolf? Are there wolves out there?
狼? 不 那不是一般的狼
Wolves? No, that is not a wolf.
奇力! 射箭!
Kili! Get your bow!
前锋座狼
Warg scouts.
这说明半兽人的队伍已经不远了
Which means an Orc pack is not far behind.
半兽人的队伍?
Orc pack?
除了你的族人之外...
Who did you tell about your quest...
你还把这次探险的事告诉谁了?
beyond your kin?
谁都没有
No one.
你到底告诉谁了?
Who did you tell?
没有 我发誓
No one, I swear.
以杜林之名...
What in...
告诉我出了什么麻烦?
Durin's name is going on?
你们掉进陷阱了
You are being hunted.
我们得离开这里
We have to get out of here.
我们没法离开 我们没有小马了
We can't. We have no ponies.
它们跑散了
They bolted.
我去引开他们
I'll draw them off.
他们是刚达巴的座狼
These are Gundabad Wargs.
你跑不过他们的
They will outrun you.
这些是罗斯加堡的兔子
These are Rhosgobel rabbits.
我倒想让它们比试比试
I'd like to see them try.
来啊! 来啊!
Come on! Come on!
来抓我啊! 哈哈!
Come and get me! Ha, ha!
过来
Come on.
别走散了
Stay together.
快跑!
Move!
欧力 停! 回来
Ori, no! Get back.
所有人 过来 快!
All of you, come on. Quick!
你要带我们去哪?
Where are you leading us?
快跑!
Move!
快!
Run!
他们在那里!
There they are!
这边走!
This way!
快点!
Quickly!
来的越来越多了!
There's more coming!
奇力!
Kili!
射箭!
Shoot them!
我们被包围了!
We're surrounded!
甘道夫在哪里?
Where's Gandalf?
他抛弃了我们
He's abandoned us.
稳住阵脚!
Hold your ground!
来这边 你们这些傻瓜!
This way, you fools!
过来 快!
Come on, move!
快点!
Quickly!
大家都来这里!
All of you!
过来!
Come on!
快 快 快!
Go, go, go!
八 九 十
Eight, nine, ten.
快点! 奇力!
Kili!
快过来!
Run!
是精灵
Elves.
我看不出来...
I cannot see...
这条路通向哪里 我们走不走?
where the pathway leads. Do we follow it or no?
当然要走
Follow it, of course.
明智的选择
I think that would be wise.
甘道夫
Gandalf.
我们这是在哪?
Where are we?
你有感觉?
You can feel it?
是啊 感觉就像是...
Yes. It feels like...
像是有魔法一样
Well, like magic.
那就对了
That's exactly what it is.
这是非常强大的魔法
A very powerful magic.
前面有光
There's light ahead.
这是伊姆拉崔河谷
The Valley of Imladris.
更多的时候 它有另一个名字
In the common tongue, it's known by another name.
瑞文戴尔
Rivendell.
这里是大海东岸最后的美丽家园
Here lies the Last Homely House East of the Sea.
这都是你计划好的
This was your plan all along.
向我们的敌人寻求帮助
To seek refuge with our enemy.
这里没有你的敌人 索林・橡木盾
You have no enemies here, Thorin Oakenshield.
如果你在林谷里...
The only ill will to be found...
感到任何敌意 那也是你自己身上的
in this valley is that which you bring yourself.
你以为精灵会为我们的探险祝福吗?
You think the Elves will give our quest their blessing?
他们会阻止我们
They will try to stop us.
没错 但是我们也有疑问需要他们指点
Of course they will. But we have questions that need to be answered.
所以如果我们想成功 和精灵的接触就需要机智
If we are to be successful, this will need to be handled with tact.
和尊重
And respect.
以及一定的风度
And no small degree of charm.
所以待会儿的谈判 就交给我吧
Which is why you will leave the talking to me.
米斯兰迪尔
Mithrandir.
啊
Ah.
林迪尔
Lindir.
注意点
Stay sharp.
我们听说你来到了幽谷
我有事得和爱隆谈谈
I must speak with Lord Elrond.
爱隆殿下不在这里
My Lord Elrond is not here.
不在这里?
Not here?
他在哪?
Where is he?
靠紧!
Close ranks!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
爱隆
Lord Elrond.
我的朋友
你去哪了?
我们出去击退了一群南边来的半兽人
我们在密道附近杀死了几个
这很奇怪 半兽人离我们的边界这么近
Strange for Orcs to come so close to our borders.
是什么人或者什么事引他们过来的
Something or someone has drawn them near.
啊 那大概是我们
Ah. That may have been us.
欢迎你 索恩之子索林
Welcome, Thorin, son of Thrain.
我想我们没见过
I do not believe we have met.
你有你祖父的风范
You have your grandfather's bearing.
索尔统治山脉的时候...
I knew Thror when he ruled...
- 我认识他  - 真的? 他从没提起过你
- Under the Mountain.  - Indeed? He made no mention of you.
生起炉火 盛上美酒 我们得款待我们的客人(辛达语)
Nartho i noer, toltho i viruvor. Boe i annam vann a nethail vin.
他在说什么?
What is he saying?
他是在侮辱我们吗?
Does he offer us insult?
不 葛罗因 他要为你们提供食物
No, Master Gloin, he's offering you food.
好吧...
Well...
这样的话 带路吧
in that case, lead on.
嘿 来吧
Hey. Come on.
试试嘛 就吃一口
Try it. Just a mouthful.
我不喜欢绿叶菜
I don't like green food.
肉在哪里?
Where's the meat?
他们这里有薯片吗?
Have they got any chips?
感谢你...
Kind of you...
招待我们
to invite us.
我都没穿正式的服装
Not really dressed for dinner.
你从来都没穿过
Well, you never are.
我个人感觉不是太喜欢女精灵 她们太瘦了
I can't say I fancy Elf maids myself, too thin.
她们都有高高的颧骨...
They're all high cheekbones...
和雪白的皮肤
and creamy skin.
我觉得她们的头发也不够浓密
Not enough facial hair for me.
不过那边的那个还不错
Although that one there is not bad.
那不是个女精灵
That's not an Elf maid.
有点意思
That's funny.
这是奥格瑞斯特 哥布林斩杀者
This is Orcrist, the Goblin-cleaver.
是由我的同族...
A famous blade...
西方高等精灵锻造的著名的宝剑
forged by the High Elves of the West, my kin.
愿它能够帮助你
May it serve you well.
这是...
And this...
格兰瑞...
is Glamdring...
敌击剑 这是...
the Foehammer. Sword...
贡多林之王的宝剑
of the King of Gondolin.
这些是为第一纪元的哥布林大战铸造的
These were made for the Goblin Wars of the First Age.
我没有冒犯的意思 年轻人
I wouldn't bother, laddie.
宝剑是以它在战争中的功勋命名的
Swords are named for the great deeds they do in war.
你什么意思 我的剑没有经历过战争?
What are you saying, my sword hasn't seen battle?
我都不确定它是一把剑
I'm not actually sure it is a sword.
它更像是一把拆信刀 真的
More of a letter opener, really.
- 你是怎么得到这些的?  - 我们是在...
- How did you come by these?  - We found them...
东方大道上的一个食人妖巢穴找到的...
in a Troll-hoard on the Great East Road...
就在...
shortly before...
- 我们被半兽人攻击之前  - 你们在...
- we were ambushed by Orcs.  - And what were you doing...
东方大道上干什么?
on the Great East Road?
不好意思
Excuse me.
十三个矮人...
Thirteen Dwarves...
和一个半身人
and a Halfling. Hm.
真是奇怪的旅行伙伴啊 甘道夫
Strange traveling companions, Gandalf.
他们都是杜林矮人的后代
These are the descendants of the house of Durin.
他们出身贵族 行事得体
They're noble, decent folk.
而且都非常有教养
And they're surprisingly cultured.
他们都非常...
They've got a deep love...
- 热爱艺术  - 换首曲子 行不行?
- of the arts.  - Change the tune, why don't you?
我感觉像是在参加葬礼
I feel like I'm at a funeral.
- 有人死了吗?  - 好吧...
- Did somebody die?  - All right...
伙计们 看我的
lads. There's only one thing for it.
# 在 #
# There's #
# 古老的灰山脚下 #
# An #
# 有一个小旅馆 #
# Inn, there's an inn There's a merry old inn #
# 老旧又欢乐的旅馆 #
# Beneath an old gray hill #
# 那里的人会酿棕色的啤酒 #
# And there they brew a beer so brown The man in the moon #
# 某个夜晚 月中人来到人间 #
# Himself came down one night #
# 在那里痛饮尽欢 #
# To drink his fill #
# 哦 #
# Oh #
# 马夫的猫醉醺醺 #
# The ostler has a tipsy cat #
# 它还会弹五弦琴 #
# That played a five-stringed fiddle #
# 马夫来来回回锯木头 #
# And up and down he saws his bow #
# 声音时而低 #
# Now squeaking high #
# 时而高 #
# Now purring low #
# 有时不低也不高 #
# Now sawing in the middle #
# 也就是说 #
# So #
# 小提琴上有只猫 #
# The cat on the fiddle #
# 弹奏古怪的歌谣 那酒有起死回生的功效 #
# Played hey-diddle-diddle A drink that'll wake the dead #
# 他锯木头发出吱吱的声音 他欢乐得不得了 #
# He squeaked and he sawed And he quickened #
# 旅馆老板和小调 #
# The tune and the landlord #
# 下了他一大跳 #
# Shook the man #
# 回到月亮上 他才说道 #
# In the Moon "It's after #
# "已经凌晨三点了" #
# Three!" he said #
我们的事和精灵无关
Our business is no concern of Elves.
看在上帝的份上 索林...
For goodness sake, Thorin...
- 给他看看地图  - 地图是...
- show him the map.  - It is the legacy...
我祖先的遗物
of my people.
我需要保护它 以及它所承载的秘密
It is mine to protect, as are its secrets.
你们矮人不要那么固执好吗
Save me from the stubbornness of Dwarves.
你的骄傲会给你带来麻烦
Your pride will be your downfall.
站在你面前的是在中土世界仅有的几个...
You stand in the presence of one of the few in Middle-earth...
能看懂地图的人 把地图给爱隆
who can read that map. Show it to Lord Elrond.
索林 不行
Thorin, no.
是伊鲁柏
Erebor.
你们为什么...
What is your interest...
对这张地图感兴趣?
in this map?
主要是学术方面的原因
It's mainly academic.
你知道...
As you know...
这样的文物上有时会带有隐含的信息
this sort of artifact sometimes contains hidden text.
你还能看懂古矮人文 不是吗?
You still read ancient Dwarvish, do you not?
是色斯文(一种基于月相变化的文字)
Cirth Ithil
月亮文字?
Moon runes?
原来如此
Of course.
这是很容易被忽视的密码
An easy thing to miss.
确实如此
Well, in this case, that is true.
要解读月亮文字 必须有和写下密码那天...
Moon runes can only be read by the light of a moon...
同样季节...
of the same shape and season...
同样月相的月光
as the day on which they were written.
你能读懂它们吗?
Can you read them?
这些文字是在仲夏夜写的...
These runes were written on a Midsummer's Eve...
在两百年前一弯新月的月光下
by the light of a crescent moon nearly 200 years ago.
看起来你们注定要来到此地
It would seem you were meant to come to Rivendell.
这是你们的命运...
Fate is with you...
索林・橡木盾 今晚...
Thorin Oakenshield. The same moon...
同样的月光正在照耀着我们
shines upon us tonight.
"画眉鸟...
"Stand by the...
敲击之时 站在灰色石头旁...
gray stone when the thrush knocks...
杜林日的最后一抹阳光...
and the setting sun with the last light of Durin's Day...
- 将会落在锁眼上"  - 杜林日?
- will shine upon the keyhole. "  - Durin's Day?
那是矮人的新年 当秋季最后的月光...
It is the start of the Dwarves' new year, when the last moon of autumn...
和冬天第一缕阳光同时出现在天空的时候
and the first sun of winter appear in the sky together.
这是个坏消息
This is ill news.
夏天就要过去 杜林日马上就要到了
Summer is passing. Durin's Day will soon be upon us.
我们还有时间
We still have time.
- 时间? 干什么?  - 找到入口
- Time? For what?  - To find the entrance.
我们必须要在正确的时间站在正确的位置上
We have to be standing in exactly the right spot at exactly the right time.
那时 也只有那时 我们才能打开大门
Then, and only then, can the door be opened.
所以...
So this is...
你们的目的 就是进入那座山?
your purpose, to enter the mountain?
是又怎样?
What of it?
一定有人不赞同这种做法
There are some who would not deem it wise.
你是什么意思?
What do you mean?
你不是中土世界唯一的守护者
You are not the only guardian to stand watch over Middle-earth.
大人 那些矮人...
他们逃走了
精灵追杀我们 我们...
我不想听借口
我想要矮人国王的脑袋!
我们寡不敌众...
我们实在没办法了
我差点连命都没了
你最好...
付出代价
很快 那群矮人就会自己出现的
传我命令...
砍下他们脑袋者 重重有赏
没和你的同伴...
Not with your...
在一起?
companions?
呃 没有 应该没人会记得我的
Uh, no, I shan't be missed.
其实大部分人都觉得我根本不应该参加这次旅行
The truth is that most of them don't think I should be on this journey.
真的吗?
Indeed?
我听说霍比特人都很有毅力
I've heard that Hobbits are very resilient.
真的?
Really?
嗯
Mm.
我还听说他们都很喜欢家的温暖
I've also heard they're fond of the comforts of home.
我听说精灵的意见一点也不明智
I've heard that it's unwise to seek the council of Elves.
他们的回答总是模棱两可
That they will answer with yes and no.
如果你愿意的话...
You are very welcome to stay here, if that...
我们非常欢迎你留在这里
is your wish.
厨房表示压力很大 我们的酒也快没了
你觉得他们还会在这里待多久?
这还说不准
不 你也干过这样的事 你肯定也干过
No, you did the same thing. It's not like you didn't do it.
朵力! 给 接住它!
Dori! Here, take that.
庞博!
Bombur!
我当然敢说 我等这个机会...
Of course I was going to tell you. I was waiting...
已经等了很久了 而且 我觉得你应该相信 我知道我在做什么
for this very chance. And really, I think you can trust that I know what I am doing.
是吗? 那条巨龙已经沉睡了...
Do you? That dragon has slept...
六十年了
for 60 years.
如果你唤醒那个巨兽...
What will happen if your plan should fail...
- 但是你的计划失败...  - 万一我们成功了呢?
- if you wake that beast?  - What if we succeed?
如果矮人夺回那座山
If the Dwarves take back the mountain...
我们在东部的防线就会加强
our defenses in the east will be strengthened.
这一步走的太险了 甘道夫
It is a dangerous move, Gandalf.
什么都不做也很危险
It is also dangerous to do nothing.
拜托 伊鲁柏的皇冠本来就是属于索林的 你在怕什么?
Oh, come, the throne of Erebor is Thorin's birthright. What is it you fear?
你不记得了吗?
Have you forgotten?
他们家族有发疯的病史
A strain of madness runs deep in that family.
他的祖父就变得神志不清 他父亲也是被...
His grandfather lost his mind. His father succumbed to...
同样的疾病缠身
the same sickness.
你敢说 索林・橡木盾...
Can you swear Thorin Oakenshield...
就不会这样吗?
will not also fall?
甘道夫 我们无需作出这样的决定 中土世界的格局...
Gandalf, these decisions do not rest with us alone. It is not...
不是你我能改变的
up to you or me to redraw the map of Middle-earth.
不管有没有我们的帮助 这些矮人都会向着那座山前进
With or without our help, these Dwarves will march on the mountain.
他们决心要收复家园
They're determined to reclaim their homeland.
索林・橡木盾认为做这件事 不需要向任何人交代
I do not believe Thorin Oakenshield feels that he is answerable to anyone.
我也这么认为
Nor, for that matter, am I.
你不需要向我交待
It is not me you must answer to.
凯兰崔尔夫人
Lady Galadriel.
米斯兰迪尔
Mithrandir.
时间或许能使我变老...
但是永远改变不了您 凯兰崔尔夫人
我不知道爱隆请来了您
I had no idea Lord Elrond had sent for you.
他没有
He didn't.
是我请的
I did.
哦
Ah.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
你最近好像很忙 我的朋友
You've been busy of late, my friend.
告诉我 甘道夫...
Tell me, Gandalf...
你是不是觉得你的计划和方案...
did you think these plans and schemes of yours...
会无人知晓?
would go unnoticed?
无人知晓?
Unnoticed?
不
No.
我只是在做我认为对的事情
I'm simply doing what I feel to be right.
那条龙一直让你耿耿于怀
The dragon has long been on your mind.
确实是 夫人
That is true, my lady.
史矛革不会听命于任何人
Smaug owes allegiance to no one.
但是如果他和大敌站在一边...
But if he should side with The Enemy...
这条龙会发挥出极其可怕的作用
a dragon could be used to terrible effect.
什么敌人?
What enemy?
甘道夫 大敌已经被打败了
Gandalf, The Enemy is defeated.
索伦被击溃了 他不可能再恢复原来的力量
Sauron is vanquished. He can never regain his full strength.
你难道从来就没想过 难道最后一枚矮人之戒...
Does it not worry you that the last of the Dwarf rings...
真的随着它的主人...
should simply vanish...
一起消失了吗?
along with its bearer?
矮人七戒中有四枚毁于巨龙之焰...
Of the seven Dwarf rings, four were consumed by dragons...
索伦坠入魔多之前拿了两枚
two were taken by Sauron before he fell in Mordor.
最后一枚矮人之戒的下落却无人知晓
The fate of the last Dwarf ring remains unknown.
也就是索恩戴着的那枚戒指
The ring that was worn by Thrain.
没有至尊魔戒...
Without the ruling Ring of Power...
那七戒对于大敌来说也毫无用处
the seven are of no value to The Enemy.
要控制...
To control...
其他的戒指...
the other rings...
他就需要那唯一一枚魔戒
he needs the One.
而魔戒在很久很久之前就已经消失了
And that ring was lost long, long ago.
它被安都因河的水...
It was swept out...
冲向了大海
to sea by the waters of the Anduin.
甘道夫 四百年来我们一直生活在和平之中...
Gandalf, for 400 years we have lived in peace...
我们小心翼翼维持着...
a hard-won...
这来之不易的和平
watchful peace.
是吗? 我们生活在和平之中吗?
Are we? Are we at peace?
食人妖从山上来到平原 他们洗劫村庄 摧毁农田
Trolls have come down from the mountains. They are raiding villages, destroying farms.
半兽人在路上袭击了我们
Orcs have attacked us on the road.
这些并不是大战的序幕
Hardly a prelude to war.
你总是喜欢多管闲事...
Always you must meddle...
杞人忧天
looking for trouble where none exists.
让他说下去
Let him speak.
还有一种超越史矛革的邪恶势力在活动
There is something at work beyond the evil of Smaug.
一种更加强大的力量
Something far more powerful.
我们可以视而不见 但是我敢保证 它绝对不会放过我们
We can remain blind to it, but it will not be ignoring us, that I can promise you.
巨绿森林里藏着一股邪恶的力量
A sickness lies over the Greenwood.
住在森林里的樵夫 改称那儿为幽暗密林
The woodsmen who live there now call it Mirkwood.
他们说...
And they say...
说什么?
Well?
别停啊
Don't stop now.
告诉我们樵夫是怎么说的
Tell us what the woodsmen say.
他们说有个死灵法师
They speak of a Necromancer...
住在多尔戈多
living in Dol Guldur.
他会召唤亡灵
A sorcerer who can summon the dead.
真是荒唐
That's absurd.
这世间根本没这种力量
No such power exists in this world.
这个死灵法师不过是一个凡人
This Necromancer is nothing more than a mortal man.
一个涉足黑魔法的方士罢了
A conjurer dabbling in black magic.
我也是这么想的
And so I thought too.
- 但是瑞达加斯特看到...  - 瑞达加斯特?
- But Radagast has seen...  - Radagast?
别跟我提褐袍瑞达加斯特
Do not speak to me of Radagast the Brown.
他很愚蠢
He's a foolish fellow.
我同意 他确实有点奇怪 因为他过着隐居生活
Well, he's odd, I grant you. He lives a solitary life.
不是因为这个 肯定是他...
It's not that. It's his excessive...
过分食用迷幻蘑菇
consumption of mushrooms.
导致神志不清...
They've addled his brain...
牙齿发黄
and yellowed his teeth.
我警告过他
I've warned him.
一个巫师老是在森林里闲逛可没有好处...
It is unbefitting one of the Istari to be wandering the woods...
你带着一件东西
You carry something.
是瑞达加斯特给你的
It came to you from Radagast.
他在多尔戈多找到的
He found it in Dol Guldur.
是
Yes.
拿出来
Show me.
听我说
listen to me.
他根本就没仔细听 我都觉得是我在自言自语了
I would think I was talking to myself for all the attention that he paid.
无论如何...
By all means...
那是什么?
What is that?
是魔多的遗迹
A relic of Mordor.
魔古尔剑
A Morgul Blade.
是为安格玛巫王所铸
Made for the Witchking of Angmar.
并随他下葬
And buried with him.
安格玛死后
When Angmar fell...
北方的人类带走了他的遗体...
the Men of the North took his body...
和所有的遗产 葬于鲁道尔群山
and all that he possessed and sealed it within the High Fells of Rhudaur.
他们将他葬在山下...
Deep within the rock they buried him...
墓穴深埋...
in a tomb so dark...
永无天日
it would never come to light.
这不可能
This is not possible.
墓穴里有强大的魔咒
A powerful spell lies upon those tombs.
是不可能被打开的
They cannot be opened.
你有什么证据证明这把剑出自安格玛的坟墓?
What proof do we have this weapon came from Angmar's grave?
没有证据
I have none.
因为这根本就是臆想
Because there is none.
我来说说现在知道些什么
Let us examine what we know.
一群半兽人...
A single Orc pack...
胆大妄为 穿越了布鲁南河
has dared to cross the Bruinen.
一把古老的匕首
A dagger from a bygone age has been found.
还有一个住在废弃堡垒里...
And a human sorcerer who calls himself "The Necromancer"...
自称是"死灵法师"的人类方士
has taken up residence in a ruined fortress.
算算也没多少
It's not so very much after all.
但对这群矮人...
The question of this Dwarvish company, however...
我深感忧虑
troubles me deeply.
你还没有说服我 甘道夫
I'm not convinced, Gandalf.
我觉得我无法容忍这次远征
I do not feel I can condone such a quest.
如果他们来找我 我就不会先让他们有希望 再失望
If they'd come to me, I might have spared them this disappointment.
我没法假装自己明白你燃起他们希望的缘由
I do not pretend to understand your reason for raising their hopes.
他们走了
They are leaving.
没错
Yes.
你早就计划好了
You knew.
不 我想这件事...
No, I'm afraid there is...
没有其他意义了
nothing else for it.
爱隆殿下
My Lord Elrond.
那些矮人走了
The Dwarves, they're gone.
大家提高警惕
Be on your guard.
我们马上就要走出边境了
We're about to step over the Edge of the Wild.
巴林 你认识路 你走最前面
Balin, you know these paths. Lead on.
好
Aye.
巴金斯先生...
Master Baggins...
我建议你快跟上
I suggest you keep up.
你会跟随他们
You will follow them.
是
Yes.
帮助索林・橡木盾是对的
You are right to help Thorin Oakenshield.
但我怕这次远征会唤出...
But I fear this quest has set in motion...
那些未知的势力
forces we do not yet understand.
魔古尔剑为何出现 必须找到原因
The riddle of the Morgul Blade must be answered.
有股势力正在暗处滋长 避开了我们的耳目
Something moves in the shadows unseen, hidden from our sight.
他们不会轻易现身
It will not show itself.
还不会
Not yet.
但他们的力量与日俱增
But every day it grows in strength.
你得小心
You must be careful.
米斯兰迪尔?
Mithrandir?
为什么选了半身人?
Why the Halfling?
我不知道
I do not know.
萨鲁曼认为只有拥有强大力量的人...
Saruman believes that it is only great power...
才能与邪恶对抗
that can hold evil in check.
但我不敢苟同
But that is not what I have found.
我发现真正驱走黑暗的...
I have found it is the small things...
是平凡的人们
everyday deeds of ordinary folk...
怀着仁慈与爱意之心
that keeps the darkness at bay.
所做的平凡而微小的事迹
Simple acts of kindness and love.
为什么选了比尔博・巴金斯?
Why Bilbo Baggins?
也许是因为我感到害怕...
Perhaps it is because I'm afraid...
而他给了我勇气
and he gives me courage.
别害怕 米斯兰迪尔
Do not be afraid, Mithrandir.
你不是孤身一人
You are not alone.
无论你何时需要我的帮助...
我会来的
小心! 抓紧了
Hey! Hold on!
啊!
Aah!
比尔博!
Bilbo!
我们得找个...
We must find...
避雨的地方!
shelter!
小心!
Look out!
小心 兄弟!
Look out, brother!
抓紧!
Hold on!
这根本不是雷暴
This is no thunderstorm.
这是场战争!
It's a thunder-battle!
看!
Look!
天啊
Well, bless me.
传说是真的
The legends are true.
巨人! 石头巨人!
Giants! Stone-Giants!
躲好 傻瓜!
Take cover, you fool!
抓紧!
Hold on!
怎么回事?
What's happening?
抓住我的手!
Grab my hand!
快 快 快!
Go, go, go!
快跑! 跳过去!
Run! Get off!
跳过去!
Get off!
- 快跑!  - 小心!
- Run!  - Hold on!
小心!
Look out!
跳!
Jump!
快点!
Come on!
抓紧!
Hold on!
不!
No!
奇力!
Kili!
没事! 他们还活着!
It's all right! They're alive!
比尔博在哪?
Where's Bilbo?
那个霍比特人呢?
Where's the Hobbit?
在那!
There!
快去拉他!
Get him!
啊!
Aah!
抓住我的手!
Grab my hand!
比尔博!
Bilbo!
欧力 小心!
Ori, be careful!
抓住!
Take it!
我抓牢你了 伙计
I've got you, lad.
抓紧! 抓紧!
Grab on! Grab on!
快
Come on.
抓紧他
Get him.
加油 伙计 爬上来
Come on, lad. Up you get.
我以为我们的飞贼会死呢
I thought we'd lost our burglar.
他离开家乡就死定了
He's been lost ever since he left home.
他就不该跟着我们
He should never have come.
他在我们中间没有位置
He has no place amongst us.
德瓦林!
Dwalin!
看上去挺安全的
It looks safe enough.
到深处搜查一下
Search to the back.
山洞往往都是有主人的
Caves in the mountain are seldom unoccupied.
这儿什么都没有
There's nothing here.
那好吧 大家生火
Right, then. Let's get a fire started.
不 在这儿不能生火
No. No fires. Not in this place.
大家休息一会
Get some sleep.
天一亮 我们就出发
We start at first light.
我们应该在山里等着甘道夫来汇合
We were to wait in the mountains until Gandalfjoined us.
这是计划
That was the plan.
计划变了
Plans change.
波佛 你守第一岗
Bofur, take the first watch.
你要...
Where do you think...
去哪儿?
you're going?
回瑞文戴尔去
Back to Rivendell.
不 不 你不能现在回去 对吧?
No, no, you can't turn back now, eh?
你属于远征队
You're part of the company.
是我们中的一员
You're one of us.
但我不是 对吧?
I'm not, though, am I?
索林说我就不该跟来的 他说对了
Thorin said I should never have come and he was right.
我不姓图克...
I'm not a Took...
我姓巴金斯 不知道当时我在想什么
I'm a Baggins. I don't know what I was thinking.
我就不该出家门的
I should never have run out my door.
你想家了 我明白
You're homesick. I understand.
不 你一点都不明白 你们都不明白
No, you don't. You don't understand. None of you do.
你们是矮人 习惯了这种生活
You're Dwarves. You're used to this life.
风餐露宿...
To living on the road...
居无定所 毫无归宿!
never settling in one place, not belonging anywhere!
哦 抱歉 我无意...
Oh, I am sorry. I didn't...
不 你说得对
No, you're right.
我们没有归宿
We don't belong anywhere.
我祝你能一路顺风
I wish you all the luck in the world.
是真心的
I really do.
那是什么?
What's that?
什么?
Hmm?
快醒醒!
Wake up!
都醒醒!
哇!
Whoa!
小心! 小心！
Look out! Look out!
滚!
Get away!
肮脏的畜生!
Filthy scum!
退后!
Get back!
你会付出代价的!
You'll pay for this!
抓住你了
Got you.
好吧 好吧
All right, all right.
放开我! 把你的手拿开! 放开我!
Get off! Get your hands off me! Get off me!
放开我!
Get off me!
我想出了一首歌
I feel a song coming on.
# 喀拉 噼啪 黑色裂缝咔嚓嚓 #
# Clap, snap, the black crack #
# 一抓 二拉 捉过来了捏着耍 #
# Grip, grab, pinch and nab #
# 梆梆捣烂继续打 #
# Batter and beat #
# 让他们结巴 #
# Make'em stammer and #
# 叫得哇哇哇 #
# Squeak #
# 绕来 绕去 远远 #
# Pound, pound, far #
# 在地下 #
# Underground #
# 哥布林城深深埋地下 #
# Down, down, down in Goblin-town #
# 呼咻 啪啦 鞭子抽打 #
# With a swish and a smack and a whip and a crack #
# 人人上了我的刑台都爱说话 #
# Everybody talks when they're on my rack #
# 绕来 绕去 远远在地下 #
# Pound,pound, far underground #
# 哥布林城深深埋地下 #
# Down, down, down in Goblin-town #
# 拿出锤子 举起钳子 带上凿子和铜锣 #
# Hammer and tongs get out your knockers and gongs #
# 在我的叉齿上你活不了多长 #
# You won't last long on the end of my prong #
# 咚咙 哐啷 #
# Clash, crash #
# 哗啦 啪嗒 #
# Crush and smash #
# 乒乒乓乓 吓得你全身打架 #
# Bang, break, shiver and shake #
# 任你抱怨大吼 没人会来搭救 #
# You can yammer and yelp, but there ain't no help#
# 绕来 绕去 远远在地下 #
# Pound, pound, far underground #
# 哥布林城深深... #
# Down, down, down in Goblin... #
# 埋地下 #
# Town #
耶!
Yeah!
好听吧?
Catchy, isn't it?
我自己作曲的
It's one of my own compositions.
这哪里是歌
That's not a song.
简直糟糕透顶!
It's an abomination!
糟糕
Abomination.
古怪 差异
Mutations. Deviations.
这地底下满是这些东西
That's all you're gonna find down here.
是谁胆敢全副武装 闯进我的王国?
Who would be so bold as to come armed into my kingdom?
是间谍?
Spies?
小偷?
Thieves?
还是杀手?
Assassins?
是矮人 陛下
Dwarves, Your Malevolence.
矮人?
Dwarves?
我们在入口那里抓到的
We found them on the Front Porch.
那就别傻站着 搜他们的身
Well, don't just stand there. Search them.
角角落落
Every crack.
好好搜搜
Every crevice.
我相信...
It is my belief...
尊贵的大王 他们...
your great protuberance, that they...
和精灵是一伙的!
are in league with Elves!
"瑞文戴尔铸造" 啊
"Made in Rivendell. " Ah.
第二纪的东西 送也送不掉
Second Age. Couldn't give it away.
只是些纪念品
Just a couple of keepsakes.
你们到我的地盘上做什么?
What are you doing in these parts?
别担心 兄弟们 我来处理
Uh, don't worry, lads. I'll handle this.
他... 他要做什么?
What's... What's that?
不准耍花招 我要听实话 毫无隐瞒
No tricks. I want the truth, warts and all.
麻烦再说响一点
You're going to have to speak up.
你的手下踩扁了我的助听喇叭
Your boys flattened my trumpet.
我会踩扁的可不止你的喇叭!
I'll flatten more than your trumpet!
如果你要更多消息 就该跟我谈
If it's more information you want, I'm the one you should speak to.
嗯哼
Mm-hm.
我们本来在路上走 不是大路啦 比较像小路
We were on the road. Well, it's not so much a road as a path.
其实想想 连小路也算不上 顶多是条小径
It's not even that, come to think of it. More like a track.
重点是 我们在这条像小路 又像小径的路上走
Anyway, the point is, we were on this road, like a path, like a track.
结果就遇到了问题 因为我们本该...
And then we weren't, which is a problem, because we were...
- 在上礼拜二...  - 闭嘴
- supposed to be in Dunland...  - Shut up.
就到登兰德的(离此处脚程约...1个月)
last Tuesday.
是去拜访远亲
Visiting distant relations.
我妈妈那边的亲戚
Some inbreds on me mother's side.
闭嘴!
Shut up!
如果他们不开口 我们就想办法撬开他们的嘴
If they will not talk, we'll make them squawk.
把绞肉机搬过来
Bring up the mangler.
还有碎骨锤
Bring up the bonebreaker.
从最年轻的开始
Start with the youngest.
等等!
Wait!
哎呀 看看 看看
Well, well, well.
看看是谁来了
Look who it is.
原来是索林呀 索恩之子 索尔之孙...
Thorin, son of Thrain, son of Thror...
山丘之王
King Under the Mountain.
哦 但我忘了 你已经没有山了
Oh, but I'm forgetting. You don't have a mountain.
也不是国王...
And you're not a king...
那你其实就是个...
which makes you...
无名小卒
nobody, really.
我知道有人悬赏了一笔可观的赏金 要买你的脑袋
I know someone who would pay a pretty price for your head.
就一颗脑袋
Just a head.
别的不要
Nothing attached.
也许你知道我说的是谁
Perhaps you know of whom I speak.
你的宿敌
An old enemy of yours.
骑着白色座狼的苍白半兽人
A pale Orc, astride a white Warg.
毁灭者阿索格已经死了
Azog the Defiler was destroyed.
他在很久之前的一战中已经死了
He was slain in battle long ago.
所以你觉得他已经不能兴风作浪了 对吧?
So you think his defiling days are done, do you?
给苍白半兽人传话
Send word to the pale Orc.
跟他说我抓到了他要的人
Tell him I have found his prize.
好
Yes.
真棒
太棒了!
Yes!
咕噜 咕噜!
Gollum, gollum!
啊!
Aah!
恶心的哥布林!
Nasty Goblinses!
但总比陈年骨头好 宝贝
Better than old bones, precious.
总比没有的好
Better than nothing.
骨头太多了 宝贝 都没多少肉!
Too many boneses, precious. Not enough flesh!
闭嘴! 把它的皮扒下来
Shut up! Cut its skin off.
从它的头开始
Start with its head.
# 冰冷的地面 磨破了我们的手 #
# The cold hard lands. They bites our hands #
# 折磨着我们的脚 #
# They gnaws our feet #
# 岩石和石块 就跟陈骨头一般 #
# The rocks and stones. They're like old bones #
# 根本没有肉 #
# All bare of meat #
# 冰冷如尸体 全无气息 #
# Cold as death. Without no breath #
# 就能吃了 #
# It's good to eat #
神还真是保佑我们...
Bless us and splash us...
宝贝
precious.
这只看上去有好多肉
That's a meaty mouthful.
咕噜 咕噜! 啊
Gollum, gollum! Aah.
退后 快退后
Back. Stay back.
我警告你...
I'm warning you...
别靠近我
don't come any closer.
他有一把精灵的剑
It's got an Elfish blade.
但他不是精灵
But it's not an Elfs.
不是精灵 不是
Not an Elfs, no.
那他是什么 宝贝?
What is it, precious?
是什么?
What is it?
我叫比尔博・巴金斯
My name is Bilbo Baggins.
巴金斯?
Bagginses?
什么是巴金斯 宝贝?
What is a Bagginses, precious?
- 我是住在夏尔的霍比特人  - 哦
- I'm a Hobbit from the Shire.  - Oh.
我们喜欢哥布林 蝙蝠和鱼 但我们没吃过霍比特人
We like Goblinses, batses and fishes. But we hasn't tried Hobbitses before.
鲜嫩吗? 多汁吗?
Is it soft? Is it juicy?
退后...
Now, now...
别靠近我!
keep your distance!
你再靠近 我就动手了
I'll use this if I have to.
啊!
Aah!
我不想惹麻烦
I don't want any trouble.
你懂吗?
Do you understand?
你只要给我指条出去的路 我马上就走
Just show me the way to get out of here and I'll be on my way.
怎么了? 他迷路了吗?
Why? Is it lost?
没错 但我想快点找到路
Yes. Yes, and I want to get unlost as soon as possible.
哦 我懂! 我知道一条安全的路
Ooh, we knows! We knows safe paths for Hobbitses.
在黑暗里的...
Safe paths in...
安全小道 闭嘴!
the dark. Shut up!
我没开口
I didn't say anything.
我们没在跟你说话
We wasn't talking to you.
不 宝贝 我们的确在跟他说话
Oh, yes, we was, precious. We was.
听着 我不知道你在玩什么游戏...
Look, I don't know what your game is...
但我...
but I...
游戏?
Games?
哦 我们就喜欢玩游戏 对吧 宝贝?
Oh, we love games, doesn't we, precious?
看上去像游戏吗? 像吗 像吗?
Does it like games? Does it, does it?
他想玩吗?
Does it like to play?
也许吧
Maybe.
什么东西有根 却没人看得见?
What has roots as nobody sees?
比树还高?
Is taller than trees?
直上云霄
Up, up, up it goes
但却
And yet
从不生长
Never grows
是山
The mountain.
对 猜对了
Yes, yes.
再猜一个 好吗?
Oh, let's have another one, eh?
对! 再猜一个
Yes! Do it again.
这回你来问
Do it again. Ask us.
不! 别猜谜了
No! No more riddles.
杀了他
Finish him off.
快杀了他! 咕噜 咕噜!
Finish him now! Gollum, gollum!
不! 等等
No! No. No.
等等 我想玩 真的想
No. I want to play. I do.
我想玩 我看得出...
I want to play. I can see...
你很擅长猜谜
you are very good at this.
所以我们...
So why don't we...
再玩玩猜谜吧? 怎么样?
have a game of riddles? Yes?
就我们两个
Just you and me.
好 好 就我们
Yes. Yes, just us.
好 就这样
Yes. Yes.
如果我赢了...
And if I win...
你就带我出去 好吗?
you show me the way out. Yes?
好 好
Yes. Yes.
如果他输了呢?
And if it loses?
怎么办?
What then?
如果他输了 宝贝 我们就吃了他
Well, if it loses, precious, then we eats it.
如果巴金斯输了 我们就吞了他
If Baggins loses, we eats it whole.
很公平
Fair enough.
好 巴金斯先出谜题
Well, Baggins first.
红山岗上有三十匹白马
Thirty white horses on a red hill
它们咀嚼
First they champ
它们跺脚
Then they stamp
然后停住不动了
Then they stand still
牙齿?
Teeth?
是牙齿!
Teeth!
猜对了 我的宝贝!
Oh, yes, my precious!
但是我们...
But we... We...
我们只有九颗
only have nine.
该我们了
Our turn.
没有声音 却能呼啸
Voiceless, it cries
没有翅膀 却能振翼
Wingless flutters
没有牙齿 却能噬咬
Toothless bites
没有嘴巴
Mouthless
却能低泣
Mutters
等一下
Just a minute.
呃...
Uh...
哦 哦!
Oh. Oh!
我们知道了! 我们知道!
We knows! We knows!
闭嘴!
Shut up!
风
Wind.
是风
It's wind.
当然了
Of course it is.
非常聪明...
Very clever...
霍比特人
Hobbitses.
非常聪明
Very clever.
啊啊啊
Ah-ah-ah.
盒子没有铰链
A box without hinges
钥匙或盖子
Key or lid
却能藏起
Yet golden treasure
金黄色的宝藏
Inside is hid
盒子
Box.
哦 呃...
Oh, um...
盒子 盖子和钥匙
Box. The lid and a key.
怎么样?
Well?
真讨厌
It's nasty.
盒子 钥匙
Box. Key.
你放弃吗?
Do you give up?
给我们一次机会 宝贝! 给我们一个机会!
Give us a chance, precious! Give us a chance!
鸡蛋!
Eggses!
是鸡蛋!
潮湿 易碎的...
Wet, crunchy...
小鸡蛋 没错
little eggses. Yes.
祖母教过我们...
Grandmother taught us...
怎么吮吸它们 是的!
to suck them, yes!
我们有个谜题
We have one...
要给你
for you.
它吞食一切
All things it devours
飞鸟 野兽
Birds, beasts
树木 鲜花
Trees, flowers
啃食铁
Gnaws iron
咬断钢
Bites steel
研磨坚石成食粮
Grinds hard stones to meal
回答我们
Answer us.
让我想想 拜托 我给了你很长时间
Give me a moment, please. I gave you a good long while.
飞鸟 野兽... 野兽? 树木 鲜花
Birds, beasts... Beasts? Trees, flowers.
我不知道这个了
I don't know this one.
他可口吗?
Is it tasty?
他美味吗?
Is it scrumptious?
他清脆吗?
Is it crunchable?
让我想想
Let me think.
他卡壳了
It's stuck.
巴金斯卡壳了
Bagginses is stuck.
时间到
Time's up.
时间
Time.
答案是...
The answer...
是时间
is time.
其实也没那么难嘛
Actually it wasn't that hard.
最后一个问题
Last question.
最后一次机会
Last chance.
好吧
Okay.
问我们吧
Ask us.
问我们!
Ask us!
好 好 好吧
Yes, yes. All right.
我口袋里...
What have I got...
是什么?
in my pocket?
这不公平
That's no fair.
这不公平! 这是违反...
It's not fair! It's against...
规则的!
the rules!
现在换个问题问我们
Now ask us another one.
不 不行 不行
No. No, no, no.
你说问我一个问题 那么 这就是我的问题
You said ask me a question. Well, that is my question.
我口袋里有什么?
What have I got in my pocket?
猜三次 宝贝 你必须给我们...
Three guesses, precious. It must give us...
三次机会!
three!
猜三次 那好吧 尽管猜
Three guesses. Very well, guess away.
- 手!  - 错了
- Handses!  - Wrong.
再猜
Guess again.
鱼骨头 哥布林的牙齿 湿壳 蝙蝠翅膀...
Fishbones, Goblins' teeth, wet shells, bats' wings...
是匕首! 哦 闭嘴!
Knife! Oh, shut up!
又错了 最后一次
Wrong again. Last guess.
绳子
String.
或者什么都没有
Or nothing.
一下猜了两次 两次都错了
Two guesses at once. Wrong both times.
那么...
So...
那就来吧 我赢了比赛
Come, then. I won the game.
你答应过带我出去的
You promised to show me the way out.
我们这么说过吗 宝贝?
Did we say so, precious?
我们是这么说的吗?
Did we say so?
他口袋里装了什么?
What has it got in its pocketses?
这不关你的事
That's no concern of yours.
你输了
You lost.
输了?
Lost?
丢了?(英语中输和丢是同一个词)
它在哪儿?
Where is it?
它在哪儿?!
Where is it?!
不!
No!
它在哪儿?!
Where is it?!
不!
No!
丢了!
Lost!
诅咒我们 唾骂我们吧!
Curse us and splash us!
我的宝贝...
My precious...
丢了!
is lost!
你丢了什么?
What have you lost?
不许问我们! 不关你的事!
Mustn't ask us! Not its business!
不! 咕噜!
No! Gollum!
咕噜!
Gollum!
他放了什么...
What has it got...
在他肮脏的...
in its nasty...
小口袋里?
little pocketses?
他偷了它
He stole it.
他偷了它!
He stole it!
是他偷了!
# 打碎你的骨头 #
# Bones will be shattered #
# 拧断你的脖子 #
# Necks will be wrung #
# 打得屁滚尿流 #
# You'll be beaten and battered #
# 悬挂到绞刑架上 #
# From racks you'll be hung #
# 你会死于此处 #
# You will die down here #
# 永不见天日 #
# And never be found #
# 在这幽深的 #
# Down in the deep of Goblin-town #
# 哥布林城 #
# Of Goblin-town #
我认识这把剑!
I know that sword!
这是哥布林斩杀者!
It is the Goblin-cleaver!
咬剑!
The Biter!
这把剑砍下了...
The blade that sliced...
一千个哥布林的头! 猛砍他们!
a thousand necks! Slash them!
鞭打他们! 杀了他们!
Beat them! Kill them!
一个不剩!
Kill them all!
割掉他的头!
Cut off his head!
拿起武器
Take up arms.
战斗
Fight.
战斗!
Fight!
他挥舞着敌击剑! 击剑!
He wields the Foehammer! The Beater!
如白昼般明亮!
Bright as daylight!
索林!
Thorin!
跟我来
Follow me.
快!
Quick!
快跑!
Run!
还给我们!
Give it to us!
它是...
It's...
我们的
ours.
它是我们的!
It's ours!
小偷!
Thief!
巴金斯!
Baggins!
快!
Quickly!
加速!
Faster!
前进!
Post!
向前冲!
Charge!
砍断绳子!
Cut the ropes!
快走 快!
Come on, quickly!
- 跟上 快走!  - 庞博!
- Come on, move!  - Bombur!
快 快 快!
Go, go, go!
跳!
Jump!
快跳 老弟!
Jump, lad!
快点!
Come on!
推!
Push!
快走!
Come on!
跟我来!
小心背后!
Watch your backs!
还想逃过我的手心
You thought you could escape me.
你现在还想干什么 巫师?
What are you going to do now, Wizard?
还真有两下子
That'll do it.
好了 这还不算最糟的呢
Well, that could have been worse.
乌鸦嘴!
Haver!
开什么玩笑!
You've got to be joking!
甘道夫!
Gandalf!
他们太多了 我们打不过
There's too many. We can't fight them.
只有一样东西可以救我们 阳光!
Only one thing will save us, daylight!
快点!
Come on!
抓住我! 站起来
Here! On your feet.
- 巴林  - 快!
- Balin.  - Come on!
慢着!
Wait!
我的宝贝 等等我!
My precious. Wait!
咕噜 咕噜!
Gollum, gollum!
快 快!
Quick, quick!
这边
This way.
- 跟上  - 快 跟上 快
- Come on.  - Come on, come on. Quickly.
没错 很好!
Right, good!
巴金斯!
Baggins!
小偷!
Thief!
诅咒他粉碎他! 我们永远恨他!
Curse it and crush it! We hates it forever!
五 六 七 八
Five, six, seven, eight.
毕佛 波佛 十个了
Bifur. Bofur. That's 10.
菲力 奇力! 十二个
Fili, Kili! That's 12.
还有庞博 加起来十三个
And Bombur. That makes 13.
比尔博去哪了?
Where's Bilbo?
我们的霍比特人呢?
Where is our Hobbit?
我们的霍比特人在哪儿?
诅咒那个半身人!
Curse that Halfling!
现在他丢了?
Now he's lost?
我以为他和朵力在一起!
I thought he was with Dori!
别怪我!
Don't blame me!
你最后见他是在哪?
Where did you last see him?
我记得他...
I think I saw him...
第一次被包围时...
slip away...
就溜走了
when they first collared us.
到底发生了什么?
And what happened, exactly?
- 告诉我!  - 我来告诉你发生了什么
- Tell me!  - I'll tell you what happened.
巴金斯先生趁乱...
Master Baggins saw his chance...
逃走了
and he took it.
自从他踏出家门...
He has thought of nothing but his soft bed and his warm hearth...
他一心只想柔软的床和温暖的壁炉
since first he stepped out of his door.
我们不会再见到我们的霍比特人了
We will not be seeing our Hobbit again.
他早就走远了
He is long gone.
不
No.
他没有
He isn't.
比尔博・巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins.
我这辈子从没有...
I have never been so glad...
这么高兴见到谁过
to see anyone in my life.
比尔博
Bilbo.
我们都放弃你了
We'd given you up.
你是怎么逃出来的?
How on earth did you get past the Goblins?
真的 怎么会
How, indeed.
这个 有什么关系呢? 他回来就好
Well, what does it matter? He's back.
有关系
It matters.
我想知道
I want to know.
你为什么回来?
Why did you come back?
听着 我知道你不信任我 一直都是
Look, I know you doubt me. I know you always have.
而你是对的 我经常想念我的袋底洞
And you're right. I often think of Bag-end.
想念我的书
I miss my books.
还有我的扶手椅 我的花园
And my armchair and my garden.
懂了吧 那才是我的归属
See, that's where I belong.
我的家
That's home.
这也是我回来的原因 因为...
And that's why I came back. Because...
你们还没有家
you don't have one. A home.
它被人侵占了
It was taken from you.
但我会帮你们夺回来的 尽我的能力
But I will help you take it back if I can.
追杀他们!
把他们撕成碎片!
才出虎口
Out of the frying pan.
又入狼窝 跑
And into the fire. Run.
快跑!
Run!
快!
Go!
上树!
Up into the trees!
所有人!
All of you!
爬树! 比尔博 快爬!
Climb! Bilbo, climb!
快点!
Quickly!
他们要来了!
They're coming!
- 抓紧!  - 抓紧 兄弟们!
- Hang on!  - Hold on, brothers!
阿索格
Azog.
你闻到了吗?
恐惧的味道?
我还记得你父亲身上恐惧的味道...
索恩之子索林
不可能
It cannot be.
这个是我的...
杀了其他的!
喝了他们的血!
树倒了!
It's going!
菲力!
Fili!
好哎!
Yeah!
不!
No!
哦 不
Oh, no.
甘道夫先生!
Mr. Gandalf!
哦 别乱动 朵力!
Oh, no, Dori!
救命!
Help!
不!
No!
索林! 不!
Thorin! No!
给我砍掉他的脑袋
杀了他
等等
Look.
索林!
Thorin!
索林
Thorin.
半身人呢?
The Halfling?
没事了
It's all right.
比尔博在这儿
Bilbo is here.
安然无恙
He's quite safe.
你!
You!
你那是在干什么?
What were you doing?
你差点...
You nearly got...
害死你自己!
yourself killed!
我说过...
Did I not say...
你是个累赘
that you would be a burden?
我说你不会在荒野中生存
That you would not survive in the Wild?
我说你在我们中没有位置
That you had no place amongst us?
我这辈子都没有如此大错特错
I have never been so wrong in all my life.
很抱歉我怀疑过你
I am sorry I doubted you.
不用 要是我也会怀疑的
No, I would have doubted me too.
我不是英雄...
I'm not a hero...
或者战士
or a warrior.
连飞贼...
Not even...
都算不上
a burglar.
前面是我们的目的地吗?
Is that what I think it is?
伊鲁柏...
Erebor...
孤山...
the Lonely Mountain...
中土世界矮人的...
the last of the great Dwarf kingdoms...
最后王国
of Middle-earth.
我们的家
Our home.
一只渡鸦!
A raven!
鸟儿...
The birds...
正在飞回山上
are returning to the mountain.
我亲爱的欧因...
That, my dear Oin...
那是一只画眉
is a thrush.
对我们来说 它是一种象征
But we'll take it as a sign.
一个好的预兆
A good omen.
你说的对
You're right.
我相信最艰难的时刻已经过去了
I do believe the worst is behind us.
-=圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/=-
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 景鲤
翻译: sharefans_笨 波特妹子 RK翔 小酥爱潮爷 Ainulindal?
校对: Mabb
-=圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/=-
特别鸣谢: 千欲 t麟 微微 柚子茶
# 巍峨的雾山耸立远方 #
# Far over the misty mountains rise #
# 我们站在与天相接的地方 #
# Leave us standing upon the height #
# 过往的景色 又一次看见 #
# What was before, we'll see once more #
# 是我们的王国 一点遥远的光 #
# Is our kingdom a distant light #
# 月亮之下 沸腾的火山 #
# Fiery mountain beneath the moon #
# 话未出口 我们即将到达 #
# The words unspoken, we'll be there soon #
# 思乡一曲 群山回响 #
# For home, a song that echoes on #
# 听过之人 过耳不忘 #
# And all who find us will know the tune #
# 有的人我们从未遗忘 #
# Some folk we never forget #
# 有的人我们绝不原谅 #
# Some kind we never forgive #
# 从未见过我们退却 #
# Haven't seen the back of us yet #
# 我们将战到生命最后一刻 #
# We'll fight as long as we live #
# 所有目光集中在 #
# All eyes on the hidden door #
# 开启孤山的隐蔽之门 #
# To the Lonely Mountain borne #
# 我们在狂风前夜驰骋 #
# We'll ride in the gathering storm #
# 直到夺回遗忘已久的宝藏 #
# Until we get our long-forgotten gold #
# 我们瑟缩在迷雾山脉 #
# We lay under the misty mountains cold #
# 沉眠于梦乡的黄金绚烂 #
# In slumbers deep and dreams of gold #
# 快快醒来 使命遥远 #
# We must awake, our lives to make #
# 在黑暗中举起火把 #
# And in the darkness a torch we hold #
# 从很久之前灯笼熄灭 #
# From long ago when lanterns burned #
# 直到今日 我们的心热切渴盼 #
# Until this day our hearts have yearned #
# 未知命运 阿肯宝石 #
# Her fate unknown, the Arkenstone #
# 失窃之物 势必归还 #
# What was stolen must be returned #
# 快快醒来 路途遥远 #
# We must awake and make the day #
# 寻找身心的赞歌 #
# To find a song for heart and soul #
# 有的人我们从未遗忘 #
# Some folk we never forget #
# 有的人我们绝不原谅 #
# Some kind we never forgive #
# 还未看到结束 #
# Haven't seen the end of it yet #
# 我们活着就会战斗 #
# We'll fight as long as we live #
# 所有目光集中在 #
# All eyes on the hidden door #
# 开启孤山的隐蔽之门 #
# To the Lonely Mountain borne #
# 我们在狂风前夜驰骋 #
# We'll ride in the gathering storm #
# 直到夺回遗忘已久的宝藏 #
# Till we get our long-forgotten gold #
# 远离迷雾 群山阴冷 #
# Far away from misty mountains cold #